<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:discourse="http://www.discourse.org/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Glazy Ceramics Wiki - Latest posts</title>
    <link>https://wiki.glazy.org</link>
    <description>Latest posts</description>
      <item>
        <title>About the The Glazy Wiki Died :(</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@jpib Jean-Pierre Prieto]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Too bad.<br>
Still, there are good pieces of information here !</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/about-the-the-glazy-wiki-died/936#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 08:29:27 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-post-1377</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Manganese dioxide vs manganese carbonate in Glazy calc</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@juliepeel]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Thanks very much Derek. Because there is a link to ceramicswiki I didn’t realise it was no longer active. And thanks for the INsta feedback. Julie</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/manganese-dioxide-vs-manganese-carbonate-in-glazy-calc/935#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2021 07:57:59 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-post-1372</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Manganese dioxide vs manganese carbonate in Glazy calc</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@ceramicswiki Ceramics Wiki]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Hi Julie, just saw your IG post and commented there.  This Wiki is defunct, you can now post questions and comments directly in Glazy by creating a New Post (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H4u6yfGKcS0" class="inline-onebox">14. Posts - YouTube</a>) or adding a comment directly to a recipe or material.  I’ve made some updates to this wiki to make it more apparent that it is dead, but I don’t want to take down this wiki because there is still valuable info here.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/manganese-dioxide-vs-manganese-carbonate-in-glazy-calc/935#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2021 15:36:45 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-post-1371</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>About the The Glazy Wiki Died :(</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@ceramicswiki Ceramics Wiki]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>This Discourse Wiki was an attempt to provide a home for Glazy’s documentation as well as support and discussion related to glaze chemistry.  Unfortunately it didn’t work out.</p>
<p>You can now have discussions directly in Glazy, just go to <a href="https://glazy.org/">https://glazy.org/</a> and create a new Post.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/about-the-the-glazy-wiki-died/936#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2021 15:28:34 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-post-1370</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Glazy Help Index</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@ceramicswiki Ceramics Wiki]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[  ]]></description>
        <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/glazy-help-index/438#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 05:21:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-post-1369</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Glazy Help Index</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@ceramicswiki Ceramics Wiki]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[  ]]></description>
        <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/glazy-help-index/438#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 05:21:21 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-post-1368</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Manganese dioxide vs manganese carbonate in Glazy calc</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@juliepeel]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I was looking at a bronze glaze by [Ruth Gillet <span class="hashtag">#4576</span>] (<a href="https://glazy.org/recipes/4576" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Glazy</a>) and amending it to use the materials I have. When I substituted manganese dioxide for manganese carbonate the resulting MnO was treated completely differently <a href="https://glazy.org/recipes/143794" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">see #143794</a>.</p>
<p>The carbonate in <span class="hashtag">#4576</span> was included with R2 but the dioxide in <span class="hashtag">#143794</span> is shown just as a colourant.  I referred to Digital Fire for the adjustment from carbonate to dioxide and altered all the other materials in <span class="hashtag">#4576</span> before I changed the carbonate to dioxide <a href="https://glazy.org/recipes/143793" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">#143793</a>, so that I could make sure the glaze was in the same general area on Stull.  The glaze looked pretty similar until I changed the manganese and then it went off the Stull chart. Why are the two materials treated so very differently in the Stull analysis?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/manganese-dioxide-vs-manganese-carbonate-in-glazy-calc/935#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2021 13:53:04 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-post-1367</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Measuring Heatwork &amp; Temperature</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@juliepeel]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Thanks very much for sharing your method, Marsha. I now have a new kiln and it seems exactly the right time to do the research you suggest here. I’ve learned a lot about this over the past few months and understand the concepts much better than before so am looking forward to some rigorous testing.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/measuring-heatwork-temperature/755#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2021 23:27:51 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-post-1360</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>R2O:RO ratio - significance?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@juliepeel]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Sorry it has taken me so long to get round to reading this paper. I was doing a bit more background reading which helped me understand it better. A very illuminating article</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/r2o-ro-ratio-significance/893#post_6</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2021 23:19:44 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-post-1359</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Flue sizing</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@ceramicswiki Ceramics Wiki]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Hi, unfortunately no one really uses this wiki anymore, it might be best to ask your question on Glazy:  <a href="https://glazy.org">https://glazy.org</a>  Here is how to post a question:  <a href="https://help.glazy.org/guide/posts/">https://help.glazy.org/guide/posts/</a></p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/flue-sizing/928#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 23 Dec 2020 15:50:36 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-post-1357</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Flue sizing</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@rcraig1724]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I have access to a wood fired soda kiln, based on Peg Udall’s design. We’ve fired several times and have trouble getting temp *10 on top.  It was built with what appear to be very large flue openings.  Is there any formula, rule of thumb for the size of flue opening?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/flue-sizing/928#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Dec 2020 05:11:01 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-post-1356</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Preparation of separative-phase fancy glaze derived from iron ore slag</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@ceramicswiki Ceramics Wiki]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Jianfeng Zhu, Pei Shin, Fen Wang, Ting Zhao, Hao Jiang<br>
School of Materials Science and Engineering, Shaanxi University of Science &amp; Technology, Xi’an 710021, PR China</p>
<p><a class="attachment" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/short-url/2aRUn67oCCkDaExUGkYazGZoAO.pdf">zhu2016 (1).pdf</a> (3.5 MB)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/preparation-of-separative-phase-fancy-glaze-derived-from-iron-ore-slag/924#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2020 04:22:34 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-post-1352</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Effects of microstructure on the sky-green color in imitating ancient Jun glazes</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@ceramicswiki Ceramics Wiki]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Jianfeng ZHU,³ Pei SHI,³³ Fen WANG, Longlong DONG and Ting ZHAO<br>
School of Materials Science and Engineering, Shaanxi University of Science &amp; Technology, Xi’an 710021, China</p>
<p><a class="attachment" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/short-url/1I8NVKNmVbzoj8nJi7Ib74qXMDz.pdf">zhu2016.pdf</a> (4.4 MB)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/effects-of-microstructure-on-the-sky-green-color-in-imitating-ancient-jun-glazes/923#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2020 04:20:29 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-post-1351</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Study on the Five dynasty sky-green glaze from Yaozhou kiln and its coloring mechanism</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@ceramicswiki Ceramics Wiki]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Pei Shi, Fen Wang⁎, Jianfeng Zhu, Biao Zhang, Ting Zhao, Yi Wang, Yi Qin</p>
<p><a class="attachment" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/short-url/50X5BER3wEWYJVssr13LlIcbOYK.pdf">shi2016.pdf</a> (2.0 MB)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/study-on-the-five-dynasty-sky-green-glaze-from-yaozhou-kiln-and-its-coloring-mechanism/922#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2020 04:16:51 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-post-1350</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Amorphous photonic crystals and structural colors in the phase separation glaze</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@ceramicswiki Ceramics Wiki]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Authors: Pei Shi, Fen Wang, Jianfeng Zhu, Haibo Yang, Yi Wang, Yuan Fang, Biao Zhang, Jiahuan Wang</p>
<p><a class="attachment" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/short-url/dLC5wN6pCxMVogCWKtJG93zzlVe.pdf">shi2017.pdf</a> (776.5 KB)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/amorphous-photonic-crystals-and-structural-colors-in-the-phase-separation-glaze/921#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2020 04:15:23 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-post-1349</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Effect of phase separation on the Jian ware blue colored glaze with iron oxide</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@ceramicswiki Ceramics Wiki]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Pei Shi, Fen Wang⁎, Jianfeng Zhu, Biao Zhang, Ting Zhao, Yi Wang, Jiahuan Wang<br>
School of Materials Science and Engineering, Shaanxi University of Science &amp; Technology, Xi’an 710021, PR China</p>
<p><a class="attachment" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/short-url/jDpjLdi11QHCYojH6ukxceUAH8H.pdf">shi2018.pdf</a> (3.2 MB)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/effect-of-phase-separation-on-the-jian-ware-blue-colored-glaze-with-iron-oxide/920#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2020 04:14:04 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-post-1348</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Study on the coloring mechanism of the Ru celadon glaze in the Northern Song Dynasty</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@ceramicswiki Ceramics Wiki]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>P. Shi, F. Wang, B. Zhang, H. Luo, J. Zhu, G. Fei, Study on the coloring<br>
mechanism of the Ru celadon glaze in the Northern Song Dynasty, Ceramics International (2020), doi:<br>
<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ceramint.2020.06.139">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ceramint.2020.06.139</a>.</p>
<p><a class="attachment" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/short-url/a4OBSHFfZKh3GDKeTng8taj61g5.pdf">shi2020.pdf</a> (967.1 KB)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/study-on-the-coloring-mechanism-of-the-ru-celadon-glaze-in-the-northern-song-dynasty/919#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2020 04:09:55 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-post-1347</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Preparation of the moon-white glaze by carbothermic reduction of Fe2O3 and SiC</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@ceramicswiki Ceramics Wiki]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Jianfeng Zhu, Pei Shi ∗, Fen Wang, Ting Zhao<br>
School of Materials Science and Engineering, Shaanxi University of Science &amp; Technology, Xi’an 710021, PR China</p>
<p><a class="attachment" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/short-url/mZIrTzyIp8o3lKPbitbHd6NLmDK.pdf">zhu2015.pdf</a> (3.0 MB)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/preparation-of-the-moon-white-glaze-by-carbothermic-reduction-of-fe2o3-and-sic/918#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2020 03:28:10 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-post-1346</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Effect of Iron Oxide and Phase Separation on the Color of Blue Jun Ware Glaze</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@ceramicswiki Ceramics Wiki]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p><em>Fen Wang∗, Changan Yang, Jianfeng Zhu, and Ying Lin Shaanxi University of Science and Technology, Xi’an 710021, China</em></p>
<p>Based on the traditional Jun ware glaze, the imitated Jun ware glazes were prepared by adding iron oxide and introducing phase separation agent apatite through four-angle-method. The effect of iron oxide contents, phase separation and the firing temperature on the color of Jun ware glazes were investigated by a neutral atmosphere experiment, optical microscope and scanning electronic microscope. The results showed that the colorant, mainly Fe2O3, contributed to the Jun ware glaze blue and cyan colors of Jun ware glaze. The light scatter caused by the small droplets in phase separation structure only influenced the shade of the glaze color, intensify or weaken the color, and thus made the glaze perfect and elegant opal visual effects, but was not the origin of general blue or cyan colors of Jun ware glaze. In addition, the firing temperature and the basic glaze composition affected the glaze colors to some extent.</p>
<p><a class="attachment" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/short-url/tgeatX1eZmLVit9BjJRTqSTRoO9.pdf">wang2015.pdf</a> (397.8 KB)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/effect-of-iron-oxide-and-phase-separation-on-the-color-of-blue-jun-ware-glaze/917#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2020 18:38:21 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-post-1345</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Measuring Heatwork &amp; Temperature</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@Marsha Marsha Gilbert]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>The term heatwork is not a proper scientific concept.  <a href="https://www.explainthatstuff.com/heat.html" rel="nofollow noopener">https://www.explainthatstuff.com/heat.html</a></p>
<p>Above is an article that explains in easy terms the concept of specific heat capacity (a scientific concept) and its interesting relationship to temperature.</p>
<p>I have evolved an experiential approach to increasing or decreasing cone results by manipulating holding time at peak temperature, or, alternatively, adjusting peak temperature.</p>
<p>I make numerous test runs using a ramp program on my kiln increasing the hold time by 5 minutes at peak temperature each run (or whatever equal increments of time you want to use).  I put three Orton cones in the empty kiln (e.g. 5, 6, 7) and measure the melt angle as precisely as possible at the end of each run.  Make certain to note the starting temperature and open the kiln after the same amount of time has passed. You should start at the same start temp each time, but that is hard to control.  Then I chart melt angle as a function of hold  time for a given peak temperature.  (this chart is specific to an empty kiln, so use it as a working tool, not a bible.) You will quickly learn how to use your chart to your advantage.</p>
<p>Then I load my kiln and run the program that the chart indicates will provide the desired cone.  At the end of the run, if my Orton cone is melted to the desired angle, I assume that I have reached the desired temperature.  My test procedure is  not quite as simple as this, but this gives you the idea.  Expect variations based on the materials you have in the kiln and how densely you have packed the kiln, etc.  I had to go through this exercise last year because my kiln was not in sync with my Orton cones.  I am now getting the results I want.</p>
<p>But to muddy the waters, There is a long running dispute about this between some kiln manufacturers and Orton.  Check with your kiln manufacturer to see what they think about adding or reducing heat energy to achieve the cone you desire and then run tests and see for yourself how your kiln is responding.</p>
<p>As far as heat capacity is concerned, you can either alter the peak temperature or adjust holding time.  However, your glazes may respond better to one method over the other.  Have patience and be consistent.  Best of luck to you.</p>
<p>There may be other simpler ways to learn the behavior of  your kiln and how to calibrate it to your work style and needs. If anyone has information to share, it will be appreciated.</p>
<p>P.S. even if you calculate the area under a curve to arrive at some values, you will  have to learn how to apply those values to your kiln and work style to get the results you want.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/measuring-heatwork-temperature/755#post_5</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2020 03:43:25 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-post-1339</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Measuring Heatwork &amp; Temperature</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@juliepeel]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Thanks Derek. I found an article on Ceramic Arts Network with a graph showing total heatwork as the area under the graph, and that made sense as an accumulated time/temperature concept. There must be a scientific way of calculating total heatwork on a material. Perhaps it is not applicable here though.</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/measuring-heatwork-temperature/755#post_4</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 14:40:53 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-post-1338</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Measuring Heatwork &amp; Temperature</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@derek Derek Au]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I’m not familiar with that approach, and I’ve never heard that heatwork can be calculated as the area of a firing profile.  It doesn’t seem correct, though.  For example, say I fire a kiln 150°C/hr to 1000°C, then I hold the kiln for 10 hrs, then finish the firing 150°C/hr to 1255°C.  The Orton cone charts only compare the rate of heating &amp; temperature for the final hour of firing… I think that’s all you can really compare…  Here is a visualization:  <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/Bm6M98BADbd/">https://www.instagram.com/p/Bm6M98BADbd/</a></p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/measuring-heatwork-temperature/755#post_3</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 14:03:25 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-post-1337</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Measuring Heatwork &amp; Temperature</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@juliepeel]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>I have been trying to be scientific about arranging my firing schedule in a small electric kiln with a controller. I understand the concept of heatwork and use cones on all shelves in my kiln to monitor results. I soak at top temperature and fire down so want to compensate for the additional heatwork these procedures involve when I set the top  temperature on my controller.  I understood that this could be done by looking at the area under a graph of total heatwork, but having compared theoretical models using the Orton cone firing tables, if this is indeed the case, I must be missing something.</p>
<p>The following example uses °C, as I am in the UK, and I am referring to the Orton theoretical temperature values.</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>In the Orton table Cone 7 is reached at 1237°C when firing at 60°C /hr, if this is a straight ramp, this would take 20.3hrs, assuming a starting room temp of 17°C ((1237-17)/60).  If the x-axis is time and the y-axis temperature, the area under the graph is a triangle and can be calculated as (1237 x 20.3)/2 =  12,555</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>When firing at 150°C/hr cone 7 is reached at 1255°C. As a straight ramp this would take 8.25hrs ((1255-17)/150). Then the area under the graph is also a triangle calculated as (1255x8.25)/2 =  5179</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>SO, these areas which are supposed  to represent total heatwork to achieve cone 7 are not the same.</p>
<p>What am I missing here?</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/measuring-heatwork-temperature/755#post_2</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 13:42:39 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-post-1336</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Utilisation des cônes Orton</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@jpib Jean-Pierre Prieto]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Une introduction à l’utilisation des cônes dans un four électrique.</p>
<p><a class="attachment" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/short-url/5zeEvOv3u5zJCYRXI8hUZFMWwPn.pdf">Utilisation cones Orton.pdf</a> (1.1 MB)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/utilisation-des-cones-orton/910#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2020 21:57:07 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-post-1333</guid>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Théorie du verre - Michael Cardew</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[@jpib Jean-Pierre Prieto]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[ <p>Un chapitre intéressant dans “Pioneer Pottery” de M. Cardew, qui explique la composition d’un verre, et en quoi l’émail est un verre … mais différent.</p>
<p><a class="attachment" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/short-url/eb86mqZudUlkTjAX1ts32A1Edf7.pdf">M Cardew - Théorie du verre.pdf</a> (488.9 KB)</p> ]]></description>
        <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/theorie-du-verre-michael-cardew/909#post_1</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2020 21:46:09 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-post-1332</guid>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
