<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:discourse="http://www.discourse.org/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Techniques - Glazy Ceramics Wiki</title>
    <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/c/techniques/62</link>
    <description>Topics in the &#39;Techniques&#39; category </description>
    
      <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2019 17:22:57 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <atom:link href="https://wiki.glazy.org/c/techniques/62.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        <item>
          <title>Marbling Ceramics</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[constance.emick]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Techniques</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Marbling Your Ceramics</p>
<p>One of the recent fads that has hit the art scene is marbling.  While marbling has an extensive history, has reappeared in painting, papercraft, textiles, and ceramics.  Artists have been using marble to sculpt for thousands of years and can be traced back to ancient Mesopotamia, Egypt, and Greece (Shovava &amp;Comma 2019).  Though it wasn’t until the 10th century in Japan that the origin of marbling began with paper marbling, Suminagashi.  Since then, it has evolved into a various patterns and techniques on a multitude of different art media, including ceramics.  Marbling ceramics can be achieved in three distinct methods: as a clay body, through slip decoration, and through glazing.  As I explore the history of marbling and its impact on the ceramic world, I will experiment with the ceramic techniques and challenges each pose.</p>
<p>Marbling began in Japan around the 10th century in the form of Suminagashi, or “floating ink”.  Artists would add drops of black and indigo blue ink to water, the blow gently on the surface to create the smoky pattern.  Paper was laid on top to imprint the pattern and left to dry.  Later on, in the 15th century, Turkey and Persia created their form of marbling called Ebru, “cloud art”.  Their methodology consisted of oil paints and gouaches instead of inks.  To keep the heavier paints from sinking, a thickening agent called  <em>size</em>  was added to water, which allowed the paints to stay on the surface and gave the artist more control in creating patterns.  Once the paint was settled on the water surface, a feather, comb or stylus was used to created intricate patterns that would then be transferred to paper.  Marbling paper finally appeared in Europe during the 17thcentury when travelers to the Middle East collected the highly stylized papers and bound them into  <em>alba amicorum</em> , “books of friendship”, the predecessor to autograph books.  As popularity grew for marbled paper, Renaissance scientists began publishing accounts of marblers’ techniques and tools which was widely disseminated throughout the rest of Europe.  In the 19th century it became a popular handicraft after being published in Charles Woolnough’s The Art of Marbling (1853) (“History of Suminagashi and Marbling”).</p>
<p>During this paper marble craze is when marbling first begins to appear on ceramic vessels in Europe as a clay body, inspired by 8th century T’ang dynasty wares.  The earliest documented thrown agateware was found among the products of John Dwight, the father of English pottery.  His research of clay bodies for agateware included notes on shrinkage rates, body compatibility and colors, firing temperatures, densities, plasticity, elasticity and strength.  Laid agateware was introduced commercially in the early 1700s by Dr. Thomas Wedgwood with varicolored clays in marbled effect created in press molds.  By the 1740s potter Thomas Whieldon improved on Wedgwood’s methodology by using white clay stained with metallic oxides.  Towards the latter half of the 18th century, the hype of agateware began to die out, but sporadically popped up in other pottery centers in the 19th century.  American agateware technology made its appearance in mid-17thcentury at a tobacco pipe kiln in Maryland, but the best-known examples came from the U.S. Pottery Co. in the mid-19th century called “scroddled ware” This was a cheap way of producing pottery which refers to ware that has been created out of scraps of various clays combined to form striations in the clay body or the addition of iron slag into clay body to create the striations.  Agateware makes a brief reappearance in American art during the Arts and Crafts Movement of the 1900s.  The Niloak Pottery Co. in Arkansas created the “Mission Swirl” line of pottery made from three different local clays (cream, brown, and grey) and three colored clays (red, white, and blue).  The clays were then press molded giving their shape (Ceramics in America).</p>
<p><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/6f9d3eafbd8a1955812f910a44630a49c742f485.png" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="fVnTtBrB1WG9M3tuhSixpCg1tFH" width="164" height="74"><br>
8th Century T’ang Dynasty</p>
<p><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/04437e9ff390b1a93609bc07b4abac976be4036d.png" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="BIw1fRgLFvqgL0dkbDVP5WmCu1" width="87" height="109"><br>
“Scroddled Ware”, U.S. Pottery Co., mid 19th Century</p>
<p><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/a6a1db115d0d8dc304b9617ecf7cdce2d16ea652.png" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="nM628fB6Zsi5AxsxNtLR1QJ7ixQ" width="154" height="103"><br>
“Mission Swirl”, Niloak Pottery Co., Arts and Crafts Movement</p>
<p>While the history of agateware is extensive, there is little documentation on the history of marbling as a surface adornment.  The difference between the three methods of marbling is: colorant in clay body (agateware), surface color from slips, and surface color from glaze.  As I explored each type of marbling, I found that each technique varies in difficult, with agateware being the easiest and glazing being the most difficult.</p>
<p>Marbling Clay</p>
<p>To preface this marbling option, it does take a significant amount of mason stain to color a white clay body.  The Vanadium color I chose made the clay body look slightly discolored (even after 100g), so I added in an additional 50g of Titanium Yellow.  Also, be sure to use the same body as a mix of bodies could create issues during firing especially if fired at different temperatures.</p>
<ul>
<li>·  Helmer Porcelain (made from large batch)
<ul>
<li>Helmer  100 lbs</li>
<li>Custer Feldspar  50  lbs</li>
<li>Roseville  15  lbs</li>
<li>Flint  25  lbs</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Combine dry mix.  Add 500g of water and blend.</li>
<li>Remove 1/3 of mix.  This will be for the stained portion of the body.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>a.  To note: you can remove more but you want the ratio to be less than 1:1 between the bodies to create a good marble pattern.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="3">
<li>Add stain to 1/3 mix to desired color.  Colorants may stain, be sure to wear proper protection.</li>
<li>Dry both mixes separately until plastic.</li>
<li>Wedge both bodies separately.  Remove portions of stained body and add to unstained body.</li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/a2dc2667366472d08201a9fe35619b2706c6c920.png" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="neJ1cIR5pAizpVOsPNaoPabJJM4" width="86" height="115"></p>
<ol start="6">
<li>Wedge bodies together about 5-10 times.  Do not over wedge as colors will become blended and not marbled.</li>
<li>Throw form on wheel.  Allow to dry to leather hard (for trimming and color reveal).  Initially your form will look muddied on the surface with no actual marbling, but after trimming off the surface layer you will reveal the marbling underneath.</li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/598319133211c581e6c8c82e3b71539bb801c859.png" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="cLRmZR9I2zNjqDopymk6MaECrwt" width="88" height="118"><br>
In hindsight, I think using a more vibrant color other than yellow would have been a better option for a clay body.  The marbling is still present but is subtle.</p>
<p>Marbling Slips (G. January, Irene, et al)</p>
<p>I have not been able to successfully marble slips on a thrown form, as of yet.  This form of marbling is easier done on slabs.  Marbling with slips, and with glazes, does utilize CMC powder with helps keep the slip in suspension to create the marble effect.  I reused the same recipe from the clay body as the slip as my color variant in this method and added CMC mix.</p>
<ul>
<li>·  Black Slip</li>
<li>Red Art  80</li>
<li>EPK  10</li>
<li>Talc  10</li>
<li>Manganese Dioxide  4</li>
<li>Red Iron Oxide  12</li>
<li>Black Mason Stain  5</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Roll slab out to ¼” thickness.  Place on nonporous plank, this allows the clay to stick to the surface without falling off while creating the marbling effect.  Put colored slip into squeeze bottle.</li>
<li>Coat slab in black slip and quickly drizzle colored slip onto slab.  Over a bucket, tip the slab upwards to allow the slips to move.  Rotate the slab in various directions to create desired effect.  Lay flat and allow slip to dry until it is no longer tacky.</li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/15ba515a8b4e6ad4de0c611158865ae24a2ea940.png" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="36dd4H6yH1utdaWEvyaEcXRoRlC" width="90" height="120"></p>
<ol start="3">
<li>Cut out desired shape and place on a plaster mold.  The timing between steps 2 and 3 is crucial.  If the slip is still tacky the design will come off on the mold.  If the clay is too dry it will crack when placed on the mold.</li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/8da7b04f4004ab167446c15221545ca59e2f88af.png" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="kd8ASaeriqgTOhoeC8Xrrj6En9B" width="90" height="120"></p>
<p>My first attempt of slip marbling, I did not add CMC to the colored slip.  This created a less than desirable effect as the two slips weren’t allowed to move together.  The colored slip remained on the surface of the black slip due to different densities.  The effect for the failed marbling was also done on a kick wheel which created the “starburst” result instead of the standard marbling.</p>
<p><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/06fc3be753044c086dc552c597f8df94e58d5399.png" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="ZNgXZIPW1mMx218YKle2f5eBDj" width="91" height="121"></p>
<p>Marbling Glaze (“The Ceramic School”)</p>
<p>This technique takes patience and constant movement.  While this form seems easiest, it was also the most unsuccessful after firing.  I am sure with some fine tuning and adjustments within the glazes and possibly at a lower temperature (was fired to cone 10) this effect will be more successful in coming trials.  It is important to note, again, the importance of the CMC powder in the glazes.  The difference in densities creates a separation between the glazes.</p>
<p><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/6cdfa6ed32d892929ca277943b727ddb9e985122.png" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="fx8JPdtgSWSYTgv6sY0d5x5Bbd8" width="95" height="126"></p>
<ul>
<li>·  White Glaze
<ul>
<li>Custer Feldspar  60</li>
<li>Gerstley Borate  6</li>
<li>Ball Clay  11</li>
<li>Whiting  17</li>
<li>Zinc  5</li>
<li>Lithium Carb.  1.7</li>
<li>Zircopax  10</li>
<li>Bentonite  2</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>·  Yellow Glaze
<ul>
<li>Minspar  40</li>
<li>Talc  20</li>
<li>Flint  20</li>
<li>EPK  10</li>
<li>Whiting  10</li>
<li>Titanium Yellow  10</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Add colored glaze to squeeze bottle for application.</li>
<li>Dip bisque ware into white glaze.  Drizzle colored glaze onto white glaze and rotate, allowing glazes to flow creating marbled effect.</li>
<li>Continue rotating, as it can take the glaze quite some time to dry and a stop in motion can cause flaws within the effect.</li>
</ol>
<p>As stated above, my before and after of this application proved to be unsuccessful.  The glazes seem to have run together instead of maintaining the effect of the before product during the firing.  The yellow also changed into a grey glaze (stain is TITANIUM yellow) with yellow and red mottling, which was unexpected.</p>
<p><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/f27e3e421e6332e059ae8864d65e9cb63667f6b5.png" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="yBc1p40Xsd7eAAlBlm1mGXRK32J" width="125" height="94"> <img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/d4677a74130376405126835ff723530d136bde78.png" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="uj0VlRxTTaaHXZeeK6wbJoCAXPO" width="126" height="95"> <img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/b2ad16f35e90ec80eb07261f209a4ba65207e304.png" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="puDPCxxRR3yMSR1fzfNnWtwcOhu" width="126" height="169"></p>
<p>The aesthetic of marble has been a long-standing tradition within the artist community for thousands of years and has had lasting effects on various media throughout history.  From the paper marbling of ancient Japan to trends of modern day, we can see the evolution of marbling through the change in patterning, the methodology in application, and the media it adorns.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/marbling-ceramics/868">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/marbling-ceramics/868</link>
          <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2019 17:22:57 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-topic-868</guid>
          <source url="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/marbling-ceramics/868.rss">Marbling Ceramics</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>A guide to throwing on the wheel</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[alf10]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Throwing</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p><strong>A GUIDE TO THROWING ON THE WHEEL</strong></p>
<p>Throwing is commonly defined as “the act of propelling something with a great force through the air.” Now in the ceramic world, “throwing” holds a whole different meaning. In this context, it is the entire activity of shaping one’s clay on the potter’s wheel.</p>
<p>Throwing is thought to be a bit more complex than hand building, having various steps one must follow to successfully complete such a task, however, it more often yields a cleaner &amp; symmetrical end result, which leads to its great appeal.<br>
<img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/72544d1db13e865d49e399399439bdbf31b7fb38.jpeg" alt="THROWING-5" data-base62-sha1="gjp2Rz1o6gFUj1qgzJcUsLSDuac" width="324" height="147"></p>
<p>This technique is most commonly used for creating dishware, including plates, bowls, cups, vases, etc. This is due to its rotating ability to create perfectly rounded cylindrical forms. To successfully create something as simple as a standing cylinder cup, one must refer to the following steps, but first, one must ensure they have the right tools.</p>
<p><strong>SOME NECESSARY TOOLS</strong></p>
<p>A clean wheel surface/ a clean surface to wedge</p>
<p>Small bucket of water &amp; sponge</p>
<p>Needle tool</p>
<p>Wooden trimming tool</p>
<p>Wire tool<br>
<img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/274ffd05e29e4c717550aaadb77dded3d550d673.jpeg" alt="THROWING-6" data-base62-sha1="5BLZJfovZZsYIaAnfSFVEpHsus3" width="174" height="75"><br>
<strong>STEP 1- WEDGE YOUR CLAY</strong></p>
<p>Before you even sit down at your wheel, you must wedge the clay you will be using. Wedging is defined as the “process of kneading the clay with one’s hands to remove air bubbles and ensure homogenous mass.” This is highly important since this step helps to prep your clay through compacting it, aligning its particles and creating uniformity throughout the whole form<br>
<img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/37ecb92649d461f2507c16f8ee862f7ca77823b6.jpeg" alt="THROWING-7" data-base62-sha1="7YJr9Yl2x1XfkyW9RDaI6mXqlrU" width="139" height="157"><br>
You want to complete this kneading action on a smooth, cleaned surface. Work the clay repetitively for as long as desired (I personally do 50 counts of kneading minimum, depending on amount of clay). Once the clay has been wedged, form it into a ball shape.</p>
<p><strong>STEP 2- CENTERING ON THE WHEEL</strong></p>
<p>I personally have seen this step done multiple ways; what I’m suggesting is my own personal tactic, so until you find a way that works best for you, I suggest the following.</p>
<p>Using medium force, hit the ball of clay as close to the wheel’s center as possible. Now you want to tuck your right elbow in between your right leg and your torso so your forearm is kind of resting against your thigh. This will help keep your hand steady while you work with the rotating clay.</p>
<p>Wet your clay with your sponge (the clay should be kept wet this entire time). If it dries out, it will catch in your hands easily and cause it to go off center. Keep the sponge wet &amp; placed in your left hand for now.</p>
<p><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/0986f10d995789955897b895f8fb0780275187b9.jpeg" alt="THROWING-8" data-base62-sha1="1mhpjxgk5qjbtBc0ehyEkbSGHXj" width="134" height="151"><br>
Using your right hand, still tucked against your torso, push the clay toward the center of the wheel. Interchanging, use your left hand (with the sponge) to push the clay downwards. Repeat this action while wheel spins until centered.</p>
<p>The clay is perfectly centered once you can gently lay your finger against it without the finger bumping in or out. Visually, it will look like the clay isn’t even moving, while the wheel still rotates.</p>
<p><strong>STEP 3- OPENING &amp; FORMING THE BOTTOM</strong></p>
<p>While the clay is rotating, locate the center of the wheel/ clay ball. Take your thumb of your right hand and place it at the center point. Apply pressure downwards with your left hand, creating a donut shape from above.</p>
<p>Push down until there is approximately 1/2 an inch of clay at the bottom. This will form the floor of your cup. If you aren’t sure the bottom’s thickness, then stop the wheel and measure it with your needle tool.</p>
<p>With the wheel spinning, pull your thumb outwards, towards yourself. Be sure to keep your right palm applied to the outer surface of the clay. Widen the opening to desired width, but be sure not to make the base too narrow; you will need to be able to fit your hand inside the opening as it grows taller.</p>
<p><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/7e928717c235f93d8933e61c8a7de43098cd3ef2.jpeg" alt="THROWING-9" data-base62-sha1="i3I5URT7znFySBAgAeQ5f4Axf34" width="191" height="204"><br>
<strong>STEP 4- START PULLING</strong></p>
<p>Keep your wheel rotating &amp; clay continuously wet as you continue on. For this next step your left hand will go inside the opening while your right will stay on the outside, still tucked against your torso for stability.</p>
<p>Reduce the speed of the wheel. Your left forefinger will go inside, touching the bottom base of the wall, lightly resting on the floor of the cup; meanwhile you right hand will touch the same spot on the outside of the cup wall. Be sure to rest your left thumb on top of you right hand for further connection.</p>
<p>Keeping your hands connected, apply slight pressure, pinching clay between your forefingers and begin to move straight upward. By doing this, you thin the walls and stretch them, adding height. Continue for desired height, being aware of overall thickness.</p>
<p><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/527a19b102b6cec334fcfa32741c57790e485cc5.jpeg" alt="THROWING-10" data-base62-sha1="bLCKAkfgSFMlR7dOcFAH3bUyyVv" width="175" height="254"><br>
Be sure to use your sponge and soak up all the water puddled inside the cup afterwards to avoid future cracking, as well as, remember to compress your lip; this includes, compressing the top gently to smooth out &amp; solidify your cup’s rim.</p>
<p><strong>STEP 5- TRIM &amp; CUT FINAL PRODUCT OFF WHEEL</strong></p>
<p>While the wheel is still slowly spinning, use the wedge-shaped end of your wooden trimming tool to trim the bottom of you cup; this includes the excess clay you were unable to pinch/ pull. Gently rotate the wheel while removing the trimmings away from your cup.</p>
<p><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/505afd9784756f8e97f221794c4a6dbbb4c9c1f4.jpeg" alt="THROWING-11" data-base62-sha1="bsR8VQY9BNmI3MJF1nXk3gOtVcM" width="177" height="197"><br>
Keeping your cutting wire as taut as possible, stretch it to either side of the wheel head on the other side of you cup. Rotate the wheel very slowly, keeping the wire slightly touching the wheel surface. Pull the wire toward yourself in one smooth motion, scraping the surface of the wheel and crossing under the cup. Now you may stop the wheel &amp; carefully remove the cylindrical product.</p>
<p>Place the piece somewhere out of harm’s way, lightly covered in plastic. The plastic will ensure slow, safe and even drying. The cup will be ready for its bisque firing once it has reached its bone-dry phase.<br>
<img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/b013525cbb9989adf134206d72c6aeec4910dd62.jpeg" alt="THROWING-12" data-base62-sha1="p7DqKkUdiUpsYl5yaixq4YafA8W" width="205" height="257"></p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/a-guide-to-throwing-on-the-wheel/839">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/a-guide-to-throwing-on-the-wheel/839</link>
          <pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2019 03:44:17 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-topic-839</guid>
          <source url="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/a-guide-to-throwing-on-the-wheel/839.rss">A guide to throwing on the wheel</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>How to make an Industrial Air-Release Mold</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[chloeefisher]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Slip Casting &amp; Mold Making</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p><em>An air-release mold has become an essential part of my work with tile-making. Below I will describe the materials, tools, and the necessary steps I use to create the molds which allow me to quickly produce my tiles. All of my methods have been taught to me by Jason Green while studying at Alfred University.</em></p>
<p><strong>Materials and tools list:</strong><br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/4daff32bbb681f491e9a3877f577782017f9d35d.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/4daff32bbb681f491e9a3877f577782017f9d35d" title="IMG_3544.jpeg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/4daff32bbb681f491e9a3877f577782017f9d35d_2_517x387.jpeg" alt="IMG_3544" width="517" height="387" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/4daff32bbb681f491e9a3877f577782017f9d35d_2_517x387.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/4daff32bbb681f491e9a3877f577782017f9d35d_2_775x580.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/4daff32bbb681f491e9a3877f577782017f9d35d_2_1034x774.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/4daff32bbb681f491e9a3877f577782017f9d35d_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
<ul>
<li>Molduct tubing - 1/8" (from RAM Products Inc.)</li>
<li>No. 8 Plastic tubing (from RAM Products Inc.)<br>
<div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/e516ac321a5df605eeb8fef4b910cea24a90db89.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/e516ac321a5df605eeb8fef4b910cea24a90db89" title="IMG_3535.jpeg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/e516ac321a5df605eeb8fef4b910cea24a90db89_2_345x460.jpeg" alt="IMG_3535" width="345" height="460" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/e516ac321a5df605eeb8fef4b910cea24a90db89_2_345x460.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/e516ac321a5df605eeb8fef4b910cea24a90db89_2_517x690.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/e516ac321a5df605eeb8fef4b910cea24a90db89_2_690x920.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/e516ac321a5df605eeb8fef4b910cea24a90db89_2_10x10.png"></a></div>
</li>
<li>Ceramicale (from US Gypsum)</li>
<li>zip-ties (4-inch ones work great)</li>
<li>2 buckets for mixing plaster</li>
<li>1/4 inch Male NPT Plug</li>
<li>Air Compressor with plug attachment</li>
<li>Thermal Temperature reader</li>
<li>Needle Nose Pliers</li>
<li>Wire Cutters</li>
<li>1-inch grid cage wire</li>
<li>Adhesive spray</li>
<li>silicone</li>
<li>Duct-tape</li>
<li>a tiny piece of clay or plasticine, etc.</li>
<li>set of 4 C-Clamps’</li>
<li>1 small screw (1-inch is fine)</li>
<li>set of 4 coddle boards (*** one of these boards must have a hole drilled out of it allowing the NPT plug to fit through. See images below.)<br>
<div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/95197004dae04cfbc2a2ed94f6fa786088747988.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/95197004dae04cfbc2a2ed94f6fa786088747988" title="IMG_3538.jpeg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/95197004dae04cfbc2a2ed94f6fa786088747988_2_345x460.jpeg" alt="IMG_3538" width="345" height="460" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/95197004dae04cfbc2a2ed94f6fa786088747988_2_345x460.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/95197004dae04cfbc2a2ed94f6fa786088747988_2_517x690.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/95197004dae04cfbc2a2ed94f6fa786088747988_2_690x920.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/95197004dae04cfbc2a2ed94f6fa786088747988_2_10x10.png"></a></div> <div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/7afad8f0253cf99176c6b9509b228c5a16cd9639.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/7afad8f0253cf99176c6b9509b228c5a16cd9639" title="IMG_3539.jpeg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/7afad8f0253cf99176c6b9509b228c5a16cd9639_2_345x460.jpeg" alt="IMG_3539" width="345" height="460" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/7afad8f0253cf99176c6b9509b228c5a16cd9639_2_345x460.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/7afad8f0253cf99176c6b9509b228c5a16cd9639_2_517x690.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/7afad8f0253cf99176c6b9509b228c5a16cd9639_2_690x920.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/7afad8f0253cf99176c6b9509b228c5a16cd9639_2_10x10.png"></a></div>
</li>
<li>Aluminum L bar cut to ~2 inches with 1/2 inch hole drilled through one side and tapered for NPT plug to screw into. (see images)<br>
<div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/b3c208acb174c9bee850565e17aab43831855296.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/b3c208acb174c9bee850565e17aab43831855296" title="IMG_3550.jpeg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/b3c208acb174c9bee850565e17aab43831855296_2_345x460.jpeg" alt="IMG_3550" width="345" height="460" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/b3c208acb174c9bee850565e17aab43831855296_2_345x460.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/b3c208acb174c9bee850565e17aab43831855296_2_517x690.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/b3c208acb174c9bee850565e17aab43831855296_2_690x920.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/b3c208acb174c9bee850565e17aab43831855296_2_10x10.png"></a></div> <div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/195b2d5f20bdfc73c25562e5c0b4c846ddeb2b0c.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/195b2d5f20bdfc73c25562e5c0b4c846ddeb2b0c" title="IMG_3551.jpeg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/195b2d5f20bdfc73c25562e5c0b4c846ddeb2b0c_2_345x460.jpeg" alt="IMG_3551" width="345" height="460" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/195b2d5f20bdfc73c25562e5c0b4c846ddeb2b0c_2_345x460.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/195b2d5f20bdfc73c25562e5c0b4c846ddeb2b0c_2_517x690.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/195b2d5f20bdfc73c25562e5c0b4c846ddeb2b0c_2_690x920.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/195b2d5f20bdfc73c25562e5c0b4c846ddeb2b0c_2_10x10.png"></a></div>
</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Building the mold around your prototype</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>It’s always best to glue down your prototype to a board or flat surface when making a mold. This will prevent it from floating into the plaster once it’s poured.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Using your C-clamps, set up the coddle boards around your prototype, always leaving at least one inch of space around it.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Screw the NPT Plug into the aluminum L-bracket and place into the hole drilled from your coddle board. Use duct-tape to hold this in place and fill any gaps between the plug and the hole with your clay/plasticine/etc. This will prevent plaster from leaking out of your mold once poured and prevent the mold from getting stuck to the coddle board.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Cut ~2inch of plastic tubing and slide it through the NPT plug. This will later be removed while “purging” the mold and holds the Molduct tubing to the end of the plug for smooth air input</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Measure the area of the mold and cut a frame with the cage wire. Leave a little extra space around the edges to allow for a snug fit later on. Bend in the outer-most wires and lay the wire cage frame into the mold. Use your pliers to re-bend the outer most wires to tightly fit against the coddle board walls, keeping a distance of about a 1/2 inch above the prototype in all areas, (bending or stepping of the wire frame might be necessary to make this happen).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Next, slide the Molduct tubing over the end of plastic tubing that sits inside the mold. This part can be tricky to work around the wire frame so feel free to remove or adjust it when necessary. Use zip-ties to tightly hold the both tubings together keeping close the the hole of the NPT plug. Then, use silicone to seal the ends of the Molduct tubing to the NPT plug to prevent any leaking.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p><em>Your mold should begin to look something like this:</em><br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/ae87abf578a3cb6cd6cc05fe8ce03e214932b8f9.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/ae87abf578a3cb6cd6cc05fe8ce03e214932b8f9" title="IMG_0895.jpeg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ae87abf578a3cb6cd6cc05fe8ce03e214932b8f9_2_345x460.jpeg" alt="IMG_0895" width="345" height="460" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ae87abf578a3cb6cd6cc05fe8ce03e214932b8f9_2_345x460.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ae87abf578a3cb6cd6cc05fe8ce03e214932b8f9_2_517x690.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ae87abf578a3cb6cd6cc05fe8ce03e214932b8f9_2_690x920.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ae87abf578a3cb6cd6cc05fe8ce03e214932b8f9_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
<ol start="7">
<li>The molduct tubing now needs to be wrapped up and down the wire frame, so get out your zip-ties and make sure that thing is sturdy in place. It’s easiest to follow the grid of the wire. For every inch, the tubing should be zip-tied onto the frame to hold it tightly in position. Be careful not to place your tubing too closely together and keep it about a 1/2 square away from all edges. Plug the end of the tubing with a screw and zip-tie to, again, prevent leaking. Once brought up and down the entire wire frame, your tubing set-up should look similar to this:<br>
<div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/ab4de504e7e04bdb112bb9a469d1dc0916e5d9a1.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/ab4de504e7e04bdb112bb9a469d1dc0916e5d9a1" title="IMG_0896.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ab4de504e7e04bdb112bb9a469d1dc0916e5d9a1_2_345x613.jpeg" alt="IMG_0896" width="345" height="613" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ab4de504e7e04bdb112bb9a469d1dc0916e5d9a1_2_345x613.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ab4de504e7e04bdb112bb9a469d1dc0916e5d9a1_2_517x919.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ab4de504e7e04bdb112bb9a469d1dc0916e5d9a1_2_690x1226.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ab4de504e7e04bdb112bb9a469d1dc0916e5d9a1_2_10x10.png"></a></div>
</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Your mold is now ready to be poured!</strong></p>
<p><em>Before mixing, be sure to have all of your mixing tools:</em></p>
<ul>
<li>Buckets</li>
<li>Power drill</li>
<li>Mixer (a metal one works great)</li>
<li>Thermal Temperature reader</li>
<li>Air Compressor</li>
<li>Timer</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>
<p>You may want to seal any cracks of your mold with clay to prevent the plaster from leaking out once its poured.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>It’s also best to have the air compressor set-up and ready to go so it’s not a worry when the mold it ready to be purged. I begin my air pressure at 20 dpi.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The mixing ratio for Ceramicale is different than the typical Pottery Plaster No.1 so be cautious! Always look to the distributor for proper mixing instructions. For my mixing, I use the ratio of 100 Ceramicale plaster to 40 water.</p>
<ol start="3">
<li>
<p>When weighing out your parts, always use cool water and sieve or use your hand to ensure there are no clumps in the plaster. Pour the plaster into the water bucket and try to get as much of it submerged under the water without having to touch it. I’ve found that walking around the bucket while dumping is pretty successful. Let the plaster slake for about 3 minutes.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>After slaking, the plaster must be mixed with a power drill for 12 minutes. Yes that’s right, 12 whole minutes.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>After mixing, carefully pour the plaster into the mold. If your prototype is highly detailed, a “print coat” might be a good idea to do first. To do this, dunk your hand into the plaster and flick it onto the prototype. Repeat this until the prototype is completely covered with a thin layer of plaster. Then, while pouring the remaining plaster, hold your pour steady over one spot of your prototype to prevent excess air bubbles. Bumping yourself up against the table can shake out some of those bubbles too.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Quickly get out that temperature reader and record the just-poured temperature of the plaster. Purging must begin once the temperature has increased another 28 degrees. This typically ends up being about 90 degrees F. It may take a while to begin increasing (roughly 20 minutes) but once it starts, it goes pretty fast so keep a good eye on it and have your air compressor ready to go.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Once the temperature is close to the +28 degrees mark, the coddle boards can be removed. Be cautious around the NPT plug as it can get a little stuck. Be sure to have your timer ready. Plug your mold up into the air-compressor and get ready for the purging to begin!</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>This part is always fun to watch. For every 30 seconds, the air pressure should be turned up 5dpi. This may take 9-10 minutes and should take you up to 120dpi. If your air compressor won’t allow that much, just bring it as high as possible. Be sure to take a cool video and some pictures of all the action that occurs. (P.S. its bound to get a little wet so try setting it up over a bucket or something)<br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/76ad4062988bd51f15dc7116dcfa73c272306278.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/76ad4062988bd51f15dc7116dcfa73c272306278" title="IMG_1281.jpeg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/76ad4062988bd51f15dc7116dcfa73c272306278_2_345x460.jpeg" alt="IMG_1281" width="345" height="460" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/76ad4062988bd51f15dc7116dcfa73c272306278_2_345x460.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/76ad4062988bd51f15dc7116dcfa73c272306278_2_517x690.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/76ad4062988bd51f15dc7116dcfa73c272306278_2_690x920.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/76ad4062988bd51f15dc7116dcfa73c272306278_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Once the air-pressure is brought all the way up, it’s alright to leave it there for a minute or two. Hopefully by now your prototype has popped out on its own, otherwise find a way to carefully dig it out while doing the least amount of damage to your mold. Take my advice that it’s best to have a perfect mold so you don’t have to go back and clean up every individual piece later on…</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Your new air-release mold is ready to use immediately upon finishing its purge! Be sure to run your mold under water to give it a little soak before every use. Have fun and get making!<br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/83ff034c5e2c5d681d0f815f8a59da6b426f8233.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/83ff034c5e2c5d681d0f815f8a59da6b426f8233" title="IMG_1356.jpeg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/83ff034c5e2c5d681d0f815f8a59da6b426f8233_2_345x460.jpeg" alt="IMG_1356" width="345" height="460" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/83ff034c5e2c5d681d0f815f8a59da6b426f8233_2_345x460.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/83ff034c5e2c5d681d0f815f8a59da6b426f8233_2_517x690.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/83ff034c5e2c5d681d0f815f8a59da6b426f8233_2_690x920.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/83ff034c5e2c5d681d0f815f8a59da6b426f8233_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/how-to-make-an-industrial-air-release-mold/812">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/how-to-make-an-industrial-air-release-mold/812</link>
          <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2019 20:28:23 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-topic-812</guid>
          <source url="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/how-to-make-an-industrial-air-release-mold/812.rss">How to make an Industrial Air-Release Mold</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Drying Your Work – From Plastic to Bone Dry</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[Sarah_Calhoun]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Drying</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Tired of spending hours, if not days, working on and refining the perfect ceramic form only to find a crack that seemingly developed overnight? Before you go switching out your clay body, take some time to reexamine your drying process. Drying ceramic work is often seen as an uncontrollable process or not <em>that</em> important. Improper drying can lead to warping which creates tension and will ultimately result in cracking.</p>
<p>Before delving into tips and tricks to create a suitable drying environment for your ceramic work, lets breakdown greenware shrinkage, moisture gradient, and some reasons why cracking occurs during the drying process.</p>
<p><strong>What is greenware shrinkage?</strong></p>
<p>Greenware shrinkage is the permanent contraction of a clay body, from its most plastic stage to bone dry. The particles of the clay body reorganize themselves to fit closer together as the water evaporates resulting in the overall appearance of a smaller form.</p>
<p><strong>What is a moisture gradient?</strong></p>
<p>The moisture gradient is the high and low water content areas of a clay body throughout an individual ceramic form.</p>
<p><strong>Understanding the moisture gradient based on your building method:</strong></p>
<p>Extrusion- The center of extruded coils will have a higher water content than the outer surface of the coils. Using an extruder can create a variety of forms and generalizing a moisture gradient for this style of building is not useful.</p>
<p>Wheel- These forms will have a higher water content on the outer surface of the walls, wherever water is used as a lubricant to aid in forming and shaping. The collection of water on the inner bottom of a wheel-thrown form will increase the water content in that area.</p>
<p>Slip cast- Forms will have a higher water content on the surface of the walls that do not touch the mold.</p>
<p>[Side Note: If your slip contains heavy particles or nonplastics (such as grog) that settle to the bottom of your form during the casting process, ununiformed shrinkage will occur.]</p>
<p>Slab- Initially, the center of a slab will have a higher water content. If the slab is placed in a mold that is absorbent, the higher water content will be on the surface of the wall that does not touch the mold. If the slab is placed in a mold that is not porous, the higher water content will be on the surface of the wall that touches the mold.</p>
<p><strong>Why are greenware shrinkage and moisture gradient important?</strong></p>
<p>Understanding how your ceramic form is drying can help you understand why it is cracking during the drying process. When your ceramic form is drying faster in one area than another, the contraction of the particles in faster drying areas will create tension and in the efforts to relieve that tension the form will crack.</p>
<p>[Side Note: If you are having problems with cracking at points of connection (such as seams or handles) uneven drying may be the cause. These connections create a weak point and are perfect for cracking to relieve tension.]</p>
<p><strong>How do I dry my work?</strong></p>
<p>All uncontrollable variables aside, dry your ceramic work in an environment where your clay body can dry evenly and at the same rate. The key concept to keep in mind is that the water evaporates from the outer surface of the walls by air or through absorption.</p>
<p><strong>Tips and tricks that you can incorporate into your drying process:</strong></p>
<p>Prop it- Propping your ceramic work on mini-stilts allows air to flow more evenly around your work.</p>
<p>Flip it- Similar to the propping technique, air flows more evenly around your work. Keep in mind that if you have a form that will generate tension due to poor weight distribution by flipping or has a large surface area that remains blocked from air flow, the flipping technique is not ideal.</p>
<p>Defend it- Lightly wrapping your form in plastic wrap or a damp cheesecloth changes the amount of air flow around your work and creates an environment where water evaporates at a slower and more even rate.</p>
<p>[Side Note: Using fans to dry work quickly can be considered as long as air is able to flow evenly around the form.]</p>
<p>Drying your work is an important process with many factors to consider. When deciding how you will approach the drying stage, evaluate your building method and the form you have created before choosing a drying process or a combination of processes that will work best for you.</p>
<p><strong>REFERENCES:</strong></p>
<p>Lawrence, W. G., &amp; West, R. R. Chapter 6 – Drying.  <em>Ceramic Science for the Potter</em>  (2nded.) (pp. 82-91).</p>
<p>Katz, M. Lecture 9 – Working with Clay Pt.2.  <em>Introduction to Clays Online</em> .</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/drying-your-work-from-plastic-to-bone-dry/710">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/drying-your-work-from-plastic-to-bone-dry/710</link>
          <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2019 17:02:43 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-topic-710</guid>
          <source url="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/drying-your-work-from-plastic-to-bone-dry/710.rss">Drying Your Work – From Plastic to Bone Dry</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>How to make double walled pots</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[docweathers]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Throwing</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p><a class="attachment" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/1e3219e2b7782084c354f540a0a6fc66bd12fff0.pdf">Puffy_Pots_How_to_Use_Double_Walled_Construction_to_Give_Your_Pottery_Volume_opt.pdf</a> (105.6 KB)</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/how-to-make-double-walled-pots/646">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/how-to-make-double-walled-pots/646</link>
          <pubDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2018 22:34:28 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-topic-646</guid>
          <source url="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/how-to-make-double-walled-pots/646.rss">How to make double walled pots</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Plaster Bat formula</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[docweathers]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Techniques</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p><a class="attachment" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/46b887847b76836e2e055df12993deb1af31f0d6.pdf">Plaster Bat formula.pdf</a> (86.0 KB)</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/plaster-bat-formula/645">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/plaster-bat-formula/645</link>
          <pubDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2018 22:24:23 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-topic-645</guid>
          <source url="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/plaster-bat-formula/645.rss">Plaster Bat formula</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Decorating like a piece of cake</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[docweathers]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Techniques</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p><a class="attachment" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/8bd17dd4f66d375bf2a604157f21043222e2aa35.pdf">Piece of Cake_ How to Decorate Your Pots Like a Pastry Chef.pdf</a> (243.4 KB)</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/decorating-like-a-piece-of-cake/644">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/decorating-like-a-piece-of-cake/644</link>
          <pubDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2018 22:20:41 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-topic-644</guid>
          <source url="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/decorating-like-a-piece-of-cake/644.rss">Decorating like a piece of cake</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Making Slip-casting slip</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[ceramicswiki]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Slip Casting &amp; Mold Making</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <h2>Measuring Specific Gravity</h2>
<h2>Viscosity</h2>
<h2>Problem Solving</h2>
<h2>Old Darvan</h2>
<h2>Water</h2>
<h3>Testing Water</h3>
<h3>RO Water</h3>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/making-slip-casting-slip/377">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/making-slip-casting-slip/377</link>
          <pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2017 13:15:25 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-topic-377</guid>
          <source url="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/making-slip-casting-slip/377.rss">Making Slip-casting slip</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>About the Techniques category</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[derek]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Techniques</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>(Replace this first paragraph with a brief description of your new category. This guidance will appear in the category selection area, so try to keep it below 200 characters. <strong>Until you edit this description or create topics, this category won’t appear on the categories page.</strong>)</p>
<p>Use the following paragraphs for a longer description, or to establish category guidelines or rules:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Why should people use this category? What is it for?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>How exactly is this different than the other categories we already have?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>What should topics in this category generally contain?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Do we need this category? Can we merge with another category, or subcategory?</p>
</li>
</ul>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/about-the-techniques-category/103">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/about-the-techniques-category/103</link>
          <pubDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2017 02:15:19 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>Yes</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-topic-103</guid>
          <source url="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/about-the-techniques-category/103.rss">About the Techniques category</source>
        </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
