<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:discourse="http://www.discourse.org/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Glaze Effects - Glazy Ceramics Wiki</title>
    <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/c/glazes/glaze-effects/56</link>
    <description>Topics in the &#39;Glaze Effects&#39; category Contemporary ceramicists are pushing the extremes of glazes.  Here&#39;s a place to talk about various glaze effects.</description>
    
      <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2019 05:05:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <atom:link href="https://wiki.glazy.org/c/glazes/glaze-effects/56.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        <item>
          <title>Dichroic Effect in Glass and Glaze</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[Ashleah_Elias]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Glaze Effects</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Dichroic Effect in Glass and Glaze</p>
<p>There are many ways in the ceramic field to create a variety of colors and spectacular effects on glazes. However, when the kiln is opened, and the glazes are revealed, the color you see is the color you get… or is it? The awesome truth is no, the dichroic effects found in ancient glass have been rediscovered and augmented. Science and chemistry have explained the ancient mystery of how something can be seen as two different colors and dichromatic effects are now being utilized in the ceramic field.</p>
<p>Dichroic comes from the word dichroism which, according to Merriam-Webster 2019 edition dictionary, is a property some crystals and solutions demonstrate when they don’t absorb, transmit, and reflect polarized light planes equally. In other words, as you observe an object with true dichroism the observed color changes according to what is illuminating it and/or according to what light is bouncing off it. When observing reflected light (or the light that is being bounced back to you), the dichroic effect will show a completely different color from what you observe when seeing the transmitted light (or the light filtering through the object). A good example of this effect is found in a cup from Late Roman era, 4th century AD (Brill, 2019). This glass cup shows a green color when seeing the reflected light and a red color when seeing transmitted light.<br>
<img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/dc5d6adff7d1fc7de3670b00902e9d16d589af10.png" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="vrrbKxuxB2Y31MzEpQ0iCWJbb4Q" width="159" height="169"></p>
<p>Another form of dichroism is glass that contains forms of rare earths and sometimes transition element oxides. These glasses only have the transmitted light qualities of dichroism. They Change color to the human eye depending on the type of light illuminating them. An example of this type can be found in Moser Glasses (Brill, 2019).<br>
<img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/4a7481542537a2b9c66f9cb8a4f5151f492c0925.png" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="aCEWwRgOc6kVs4dm5lyiZsRgx0h" width="147" height="154"><br>
The more modern form of what we call dichroic is a bit removed from true dichroism, in that it is an interference filter adapted from a vacuum thin film deposition process discovered in 1887, and used by scientists at NASA in the 1950’s and 1960’s (Sandberg, 2019). It is a sort of scientific cheat in that they created a screen that blocks the passage of certain directional light waves. These glasses were layered with extremely thin films of metal oxides in order to shield the instruments on space craft from cosmic radiation and the eyes of astronauts from unfiltered sunlight (High Tech Art, 1993). Today there are many wider applications for dichroic films including fiber optics, laser guidance systems, art glass, and much more (Sandberg, 2019).<br>
<img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/7c5abfd577c76b67187818513d4681b510f11b69.jpeg" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="hK5DqunFR4FQ9i1ByH8gsPPmZhT" width="188" height="169"><br>
In the mid 70’s an artist and engineer named Murray Schwartz was dumpster diving for rejected aerospace mirrors behind a GM Vacuum Coating Laboratory in Newport Beach, when he was confronted by an employee named Jerry Sandberg. This chance encounter led the two men to a research partnership that culminated in the first three dichroic color specific coatings. These color specific mirrors were spectacular however creating them was costly.<br>
<img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/01b46bd3fb6dfafd625f814ef1b305330a2b9312.jpeg" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="f51K4NjkcJTxCz8iBGkdXWxjGy" width="258" height="246"><br>
Eventually Schwartz ‘s wife, a glass fusing artist named Rupama, used a piece of their coated mirror glass in one of her glass fusing’s and the spectacular results spurred further experimentation with using dichroic coatings for other art applications and contributed to a flourishing business, selling dichroic coated glass to artists (Sandberg, 2019). The techniques Schwartz and Sandburg developed for achieving a wide range of colors in their dichroic glass are described on the Coatings by Sandberg website.</p>
<p>A breakthrough came for ceramic artists when Coatings by Sandberg introduced a product that separates the dichroic flash from its substrate creating a fine film on copper that can be removed and crushed into glitter to be applied directly to glass, plastic, and porcelain.</p>
<p>In an article written by John Conrad for Ceramic Arts Daily, Conrad shares different techniques for <a href="https://ceramicartsnetwork.org/pottery-making-illustrated/pottery-making-techniques/ceramic-decorating-techniques/glitter-flashing/#" rel="nofollow noopener">applying dichroic film to ceramic pottery</a>. This way of creating a dichroic effect on glaze uses dichroic glitter with a glue like medium of CMC Gum and water to stick the particles on to the surface of a finished piece of pottery. Once the CMC Gum is dry, a layer of clear glaze is carefully sprayed to cover the dichroic film and the piece is re-fired. The results from this create vessels with floating flecks of dichroic metal oxides sandwiched between layers of glaze. The results are more visible when applying the colorful metallic glitter to a glazed surface as they tend to be very subdued on white porcelain (Conrad, 2015).<img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/c01fbc173f1463504ae39c96f39f73f9a69a5df9.jpeg" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="rpBFgQ39iEn7AUo2E6GyxQWb4Zr" width="562" height="614"></p>
<p>The dichroic effect can also be achieved in creating glazes through an understanding of crystal field theory. A glaze formulation and technical manual for dichroic glazes, written by Jenn Wicks and Ryan Coppage, describes crystal field theory as a way of understanding electron valence systems that allows us to “change the color properties of a metal colorant or pigment based on the splitting of energy between orbitals”. In their book,  <em>The Mechanism of (and Recipes for) Dichroic Glazes</em>  (2019), Wicks and Coppage explain that,</p>
<p>The way in which we perceive the colors of transition metals has to do with how   photons (light) are absorbed [… ] Essentially, the surrounding glaze environment   encapsulates a metal, and oxygen atoms (or other components in the recipe) coordinate   themselves around the metal – typically in an octahedral or tetrahedral geometry. Based   on identity and arrangement of the surroundings, the electrons in the different d-orbitals   can experience energy repulsions, which causes a split in energy between the existing   orbitals. Such a change in energy, due to electrons not filling every orbital, allows for the   absorption of light of specific frequencies (photons); the rest is reflected off of the   surface, transmitted back to our eye, and is rebuilt into the color we see (p.147).</p>
<p>In their manual, Wicks and Coppage explore the dichroic responses rare earth oxides (neodymium oxide, erbium oxide, holmium oxide, and praseodymium oxide) have across different light sources. Their work shows that Neodymium oxide and Holmium oxide are the two rare earth oxides that have the most noticeable differences in color across different light sources when used in glaze formulations.<br>
<img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/86be5f4bf6525cecaee6a0b7c53fa501afc3b381.jpeg" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="jdZQNYx2yqwTQCYPSmEGkeerQe5" width="644" height="514"> <a href="https://www.mansfieldceramics.com/cap-articles/the-mechanism-of-and-recipes-for-dichroic-glazes/" rel="nofollow noopener">https://www.mansfieldceramics.com/cap-articles/the-mechanism-of-and-recipes-for-dichroic-glazes/</a><br>
From mysterious origins in ancient glassware where tiny amounts of colloidal gold and/or silver created a mystical color changing cup, to rare earth and transition element oxides, in the late 1800’s, creating radiation and light spectrum protection for astronauts, dichroic effects have captivated scientists and artists alike. Modern glaze chemistry and vacuum thin film deposition have enabled us to branch out of glass and into many other mediums with the spectacular and colorful effects of dichroism. When color variation, crystal formation, and the various textures of glazing aren’t enough, artists and potters alike can now enjoy the ambiguity of color like that of “the dress” only with much crisper and less ambiguous color shifts than washed out blue and black and with many more color options.<br>
<img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/fdb06c70c9ceda5aa1eab2620b052d74ce35d850.jpeg" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="AceMIKrhWEopCQTlBkqEJgCWPzW" width="236" height="360"></p>
<p>References</p>
<p>Dr. Brill, R. (2019). What is dichroic glass? - Ask a Glass Question. Corning Museum of Glass website:</p>
<p><em>High Tech Art: Chameleon Glass</em> . (1993).</p>
<p>Howard Sandberg. (2019).  <em>Dichroic Glass</em> .</p>
<p>John W. Conrad. (2015). In the Studio: Glitter Flashing. Ceramic Arts Network</p>
<p>Wicks, J. &amp; Coppage, R. (2019) The Mechanism of (and recipes for) Dichroic Glazes. Mansfield Ceramics</p>
<p>What is the Difference Between Opal, Dichroic and Opalescent Glass? (2014). Ancient Glass Blog of The Allaire Collection</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/dichroic-effect-in-glass-and-glaze/867">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/dichroic-effect-in-glass-and-glaze/867</link>
          <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2019 05:05:20 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-topic-867</guid>
          <source url="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/dichroic-effect-in-glass-and-glaze/867.rss">Dichroic Effect in Glass and Glaze</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Oil Spot Glazes</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[racheldavis]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Glaze Effects</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Oil Spot Glazes</p>
<p>Rachel Davis<br>
Glaze Formulation<br>
Matt Katz<br>
August 9th, 2019</p>
<p>The aesthetic of the oil spot glaze has been captivating viewers since it was developed during the Song Dynasty (960-1279 CE) in the Fujian province of China. Tea bowls with this highly prized surface were traded throughout east Asia, and the Japanese began developing their own glazes to mimic them.<a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[1]</a>In Japan, they were called Temmoku in reference to the Chinese mountain range Tianmu Shan. Generally speaking, the image that comes to mind when referring to a Temmoku glaze, is a deep brown or black that breaks over edges with a lighter reddish brown. But Temmoku can also refer to an entire glaze category, which includes glazes with striking effects such as the oil spot.<a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[2]</a>The potters of the Jianyang kilns in the Fujian province had specific methods for achieving this alluring glaze, which have been deciphered through excavation and analysis of sherds from the original kilns. Before attempting to understand how to create oil spot glazes today with modern technology, it is imperative to learn about this history and their technical choices. Much of the knowledge they had can be applied or modified to suit the needs of the modern potter.</p>
<p>In 2014, Pamela Vandiver and Chandra Reedy published an article on their findings from analyzing 30 sherds excavated by J.M. Plumer in 1935, from three kilns in Jianyang. They were able to determine information about glaze composition, application, and the firing process. It is important to note that the pieces they analyzed were not exclusively oil spots, but also included hare’s fur glazes. The significance of this fact is that no variation was found between the two in terms of glaze composition, meaning that the difference in the end product was due to variations in the firing process. All the glaze samples had a high iron content with calcium oxides, which had been applied to an iron-heavy body.<a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[3]</a>A high percentage of iron is one of the major keys to producing an oil spot glaze. When red iron oxide (Fe2O3) is heated, it converts to black iron oxide (FeO), releasing oxygen in the process. The calcium that is present in the glaze aids in breaking apart the iron and the oxygen.<a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[4]</a>When the oxygen bursts the surface of the glaze, it creates a crater. This occurrence is normally avoided by putting high iron glazes through an early reduction during the firing process. Starving the kiln of oxygen forces the chemically bonded oxygen in the red iron oxide to be released. When this happens before the glaze has begun melting, no oxygen bubbles will form and burst through the surface.<a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[5]</a>However, this “glaze flaw” is essential for creating the oil spot effect, which is why they must be fired in oxidation. The red iron oxide molecule will naturally release oxygen atoms at about 1230°C. This disrupts the homogeneity of the glaze, causing what is called phase separation.<a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[6]</a>When the oxygen leaves the glaze, a “spot” of iron remains.<a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[7]</a>As the firing continues, a layer of silica covers the blemished area, healing it. The potters in Jianyang had to be meticulous in their glaze application and firing techniques because viscosity and thickness plays an important role during this part of the glaze development in the kiln. Glaze thickness was around 3mm or more. If the glaze was applied too thinly, it would not produce a successful oil spot effect.<a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[8]</a>A certain balance must be achieved with the glaze viscosity. It must be stiff enough not to run, taking the iron spots with it. On the other hand, it cannot be so viscous that the oxygen bubbles fail to break the surface.<a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[9]</a>Historically these wares were glazed as greenware, placed on setters, and protected with a saggar as they were fired to 1230-1300°C. The saggar served to regulate both the temperature and the oxidation state.<a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[10]</a></p>
<p>Today, it is more common to apply the glaze to bisque ware rather than leather hard pots for increased durability during the final firing. And although the saggar method is still valid, it is not always necessary. For example, firing in an electric kiln provides an oxidation atmosphere without the threat of debris from the firing melting onto the surface. Another major development in recent years is the ability to obtain an oil spot effect with mid-range firing, albeit with some drawbacks. Spotting at this temperature tends to be smaller because of the lower temperature.<a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[11]</a>Another method for obtaining the oil spot look that works for both mid-range and high fire temperatures is using a slip-based glaze with a cover coat glaze. In this scenario, the cover glaze must melt first so the oxygen bubble can burst through it.<a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[12]</a>Traditional oil spot glazes tend to be variations of brown or black depending on the colorant. Brown, rusty colored spots come from iron oxide and darker blacks come from the addition of cobalt carbonate.<a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[13]</a>Although the cover glaze method is not the traditional way of creating the oil spot aesthetic, it uses the same principle of forming two glasses at different times during the firing. One glass must create bubbles to break through the other before it heals over. The difference here is that the two glasses come from two different glazes and is not due to phase separation of one glaze. This alternation in the process makes it simpler to explore a wider range of color possibilities with the cover coat.<a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[14]</a>Another interesting oil spot development is the usage of opacifiers such as zirconium silicate in glaze recipes. When the bubble bursts, the opacifier collects in the crater, creating white spots.<a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[15]</a>This goes to show how a bit of knowledge and creativity can create a whole new branch of a glaze type.</p>
<p>During the Song Dynasty, the Jianyang potters mastered the oil spot glaze using the resources they had. The foundation of knowledge they amassed is one that potters continue to build on today. In the modern world, we are not limited to local materials as they were. Material accessibility makes it possible to explore the potential of oil spot glazes in ways that could not be done before. Continuing to analyze ceramics of the past while testing new glaze formulas and firing methods is certain to lead to more exciting developments for oil spot glazes in the future.</p>
<p>Bibliography</p>
<p>Britt, John. “Oil-spot Glazes.”  <em>Ceramics Technical</em> , no. 21 (2005): 15-18.</p>
<p>Britt, John. 2004.  <em>The Complete Guide to High-Fire Glazes: Glazing &amp; Firing at Cone   10.</em> New York: Lark Books.</p>
<p>Britt, John. 2014. <em>The Complete Guide to Mid-Range Glazes: Glazing &amp; Firing at Cones  4-7.</em> New York: Lark Books.</p>
<p>Hansen, Tony. “Phase Separation.”  <em>Digitalfire.</em> Accessed August 08, 2019.   <a href="https://digitalfire.com/4sight/glossary/glossary_phase_separation.html" rel="nofollow noopener">https://digitalfire.com/4sight/glossary/glossary_phase_separation.html</a>.</p>
<p>Katz, Matt, and Mackenzie McDonald. Glaze formula and Test Tiles. March 08, 2019.   Raw data. Alfred University, Alfred, New York.</p>
<p>Instagram post by <span class="mention">@ceramicmaterialsworkshop</span>.</p>
<p>Katz, Matt. “Special Effects.” Lecture, Glaze Formulation Online, August 06, 2019.</p>
<p>Vandiver, Pamela B., and Chandra L. Reedy. “Traditional Craftsmanship and   Technology of Jianyang Black Wares from Fujian, China.”  <em>Studies in   Conservation</em> , no. 59 sup1 (2014): S169-S172.</p>
<p>Vickery, Frank R. “A Potters Oil-spot Marx.” Master’s thesis, Western Carolina   University, 2012.</p>
<p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[1]</a>Vandiver, Pamela B., and Chandra L. Reedy. “Traditional Craftsmanship and Technology of Jianyang Black Wares from Fujian, China.”  <em>Studies in Conservation</em> , no. 59 sup1 (2014): S169-S172, S169.</p>
<p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[2]</a>Britt, John. 2004.  <em>The Complete Guide to High-Fire Glazes: Glazing &amp; Firing at Cone 10.</em> New York: Lark Books, 70.</p>
<p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[3]</a>Vandiver and Reedy. "Traditional Craftsmanship,” S169.</p>
<p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[4]</a>Vickery, Frank R. “A Potters Oil-spot Marx.” Master’s thesis, Western Carolina University, 2012, 22.</p>
<p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[5]</a>Katz, Matt. “Special Effects.” Lecture, Glaze Formulation Online, August 06, 2019.</p>
<p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[6]</a>Hansen, Tony. “Phase Separation.”  <em>Digitalfire.</em> Accessed August 08, 2019. <a href="https://digitalfire.com/4sight/glossary/glossary_phase_separation.html" rel="nofollow noopener">https://digitalfire.com/4sight/glossary/glossary_phase_separation.html</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[7]</a>Britt, John. “Oil-spot Glazes.” Ceramics Technical, no. 21 (2005): 15-18, 16.</p>
<p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[8]</a> Vickery. “A Potters Oil-spot Marx,” 21-22.</p>
<p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[9]</a>Britt.  <em>The Complete Guide to High-Fire,</em>  75-76.</p>
<p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[10]</a>Vandiver and Reedy. "Traditional Craftsmanship,” S170.</p>
<p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[11]</a>Britt, John. 2014. <em>The Complete Guide to Mid-Range Glazes: Glazing &amp; Firing at Cones 4-7.</em> New York: Lark Books, 89.</p>
<p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[12]</a>Vickery. “A Potters Oil-spot Marx,” 23.</p>
<p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[13]</a>Britt.  <em>The Complete Guide to High-Fire,</em>  75.</p>
<p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[14]</a>Britt. “Oil-spot Glazes,” 18.</p>
<p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org">[15]</a>Katz, Matt, and Mackenzie McDonald. Glaze formula and Test Tiles. March 08, 2019. Raw data. Alfred University, Alfred, New York. Instagram post by <span class="mention">@ceramicmaterialsworkshop</span>.</p>
            <p><small>2 posts - 2 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/oil-spot-glazes/842">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/oil-spot-glazes/842</link>
          <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2019 02:15:33 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-topic-842</guid>
          <source url="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/oil-spot-glazes/842.rss">Oil Spot Glazes</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Reflective Glazes: Mirror Black</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[bre]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Glaze Effects</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Mirror Black recipe is found to be have the best reflective properties as the recipe is found on <a href="https://glazy.org/recipes/11043" rel="nofollow noopener">Glazy</a>. After altering many different aspects of the recipe the original seems to work the best for what I was using it for in reflecting neon tube lighting. It has great reactions on non-flat surfaces in altering the light. Applied by dipping or brush strokes did not seem to affect the effect by much as long as it is applied thick either way. When thin, Mirror Black it not reflective and is a brown color.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/reflective-glazes-mirror-black/810">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/reflective-glazes-mirror-black/810</link>
          <pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2019 03:36:42 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-topic-810</guid>
          <source url="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/reflective-glazes-mirror-black/810.rss">Reflective Glazes: Mirror Black</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>A little woodash</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[laura99]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Glaze Effects</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p><a href="https://alfred0-my.sharepoint.com/:w:/g/personal/lj5_alfred_edu/EXHZHgTM-sZDtNEDO6WVj6ABCFUdh6nnHsIgKvma04YAIg?e=96lEKB" rel="nofollow noopener">a little something about ash!</a></p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/a-little-woodash/739">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/a-little-woodash/739</link>
          <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2019 00:05:39 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-topic-739</guid>
          <source url="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/a-little-woodash/739.rss">A little woodash</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Firing Cone 10 Reduction in a Small Gas Kiln, &quot;Meatball&quot;</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[derek]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Glaze Effects</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <h1>Introduction to Meatball</h1>
<p></p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/7e74e1e6e4392f7d75825fb76b464d983e913ea9.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/7e74e1e6e4392f7d75825fb76b464d983e913ea9" title="IMG_8590.JPG"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/7e74e1e6e4392f7d75825fb76b464d983e913ea9_2_690x517.jpeg" alt="IMG_8590" width="690" height="517" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/7e74e1e6e4392f7d75825fb76b464d983e913ea9_2_690x517.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/7e74e1e6e4392f7d75825fb76b464d983e913ea9_2_1035x775.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/7e74e1e6e4392f7d75825fb76b464d983e913ea9_2_1380x1034.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/7e74e1e6e4392f7d75825fb76b464d983e913ea9_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
<p>Meatball is a small gas-fired downdraft kiln.  In downdraft kilns, burners force in flame through the bottom of the kiln, after which the flame travels upward and then circulates back downward, exiting through the exit flue at the bottom of the kiln.</p>
<p><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/f6fc1a59d3f874eb37e77e2c7e63ead7a1f4ce77.png" alt="kilns" width="655" height="233"><br>
(From <a href="https://www.colorado.edu/classics/2018/06/14/ancient-greek-ceramic-kilns" rel="nofollow noopener">https://www.colorado.edu/classics/2018/06/14/ancient-greek-ceramic-kilns</a>)</p>
<h1>The Burners</h1>
<p>Meatball has 2 forced air burners, paired with 2 small venturi burners which serve as <strong>safety pilot lights</strong>.  The pilots include a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thermocouple" rel="nofollow noopener">thermocouple</a> which detects heat.  If the pilots go out, the thermocouples will detect the temperature change and the <strong>safety Baso valve</strong> will automatically shut off the gas.  The pilot lights are also used to initially warm up the kiln slowly when starting the firing.</p>
<p></p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/49f6b93274b640fcdee091a7a48edc99b368714e.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/49f6b93274b640fcdee091a7a48edc99b368714e" title="kilnparts.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/49f6b93274b640fcdee091a7a48edc99b368714e_2_690x459.jpeg" alt="kilnparts" width="690" height="459" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/49f6b93274b640fcdee091a7a48edc99b368714e_2_690x459.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/49f6b93274b640fcdee091a7a48edc99b368714e_2_1035x688.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/49f6b93274b640fcdee091a7a48edc99b368714e_2_1380x918.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/49f6b93274b640fcdee091a7a48edc99b368714e_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
<h3>Forced Air Burners.</h3>
<p>These are the powerful burners that are used to fire the kiln.  They are two ways to control them:  By adjusting the gas or by adjusting the air.</p>
<p></p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/4b0393ff8bbc31e8cc798e6edb0f3e1cbe13d42f.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/4b0393ff8bbc31e8cc798e6edb0f3e1cbe13d42f" title="MB_Operating_Instructions-1.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/4b0393ff8bbc31e8cc798e6edb0f3e1cbe13d42f_2_690x540.jpeg" alt="MB_Operating_Instructions-1" width="690" height="540" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/4b0393ff8bbc31e8cc798e6edb0f3e1cbe13d42f_2_690x540.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/4b0393ff8bbc31e8cc798e6edb0f3e1cbe13d42f_2_1035x810.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/4b0393ff8bbc31e8cc798e6edb0f3e1cbe13d42f_2_1380x1080.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/4b0393ff8bbc31e8cc798e6edb0f3e1cbe13d42f_2_10x10.png"></a></div><br>
(Image from Ward Burner <a href="http://www.wardburner.com" rel="nofollow noopener">http://www.wardburner.com</a>)<p></p>
<h3>Safety Pilot Lights (Small Venturi Burners)</h3>
<p>In this kiln, 2 small venturi burners are used as “pilot” burners.  These burners include a thermocouple.  If the pilots go out, the thermocouple will detect the temperature change and <strong>shut off the gas</strong>.<br>
<img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/054a84fab6ec01b2f29c89c292c0f81aecb5e84c.jpeg" alt="V_1_MIXER_3" width="373" height="392"></p>
<h1>Loading the Kiln</h1>
<ol>
<li>
<p>Adjust the kiln bagwall and target bricks if necessary.  Record the arrangement of the bagwall and target bricks for later firings.<br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/db809de4fa1dfdf798750bbbcdba11d19e95ebff.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/db809de4fa1dfdf798750bbbcdba11d19e95ebff" title="SON09578.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/db809de4fa1dfdf798750bbbcdba11d19e95ebff_2_690x459.jpeg" alt="SON09578" width="690" height="459" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/db809de4fa1dfdf798750bbbcdba11d19e95ebff_2_690x459.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/db809de4fa1dfdf798750bbbcdba11d19e95ebff_2_1035x688.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/db809de4fa1dfdf798750bbbcdba11d19e95ebff_2_1380x918.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/db809de4fa1dfdf798750bbbcdba11d19e95ebff_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I’ve been placing a brick over the top half of the exit flue, which seems to work well but is just my “hunch” and not backed by a good comparison test.<br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/f6f35e5623a470b5dedfb6b593352187025956f5.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/f6f35e5623a470b5dedfb6b593352187025956f5" title="SON09582.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/f6f35e5623a470b5dedfb6b593352187025956f5_2_690x459.jpeg" alt="SON09582" width="690" height="459" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/f6f35e5623a470b5dedfb6b593352187025956f5_2_690x459.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/f6f35e5623a470b5dedfb6b593352187025956f5_2_1035x688.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/f6f35e5623a470b5dedfb6b593352187025956f5_2_1380x918.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/f6f35e5623a470b5dedfb6b593352187025956f5_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Ideally, put two sets of cone packs in the kiln, one at the bottom and one at the top.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Here is a fully-loaded kiln.  3 bricks are used per level.<br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/1aec020164c4cd30cb05a7e9d07b8038393fc93d.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/1aec020164c4cd30cb05a7e9d07b8038393fc93d" title="IMG_8587.JPG"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/1aec020164c4cd30cb05a7e9d07b8038393fc93d_2_690x920.jpeg" alt="IMG_8587" width="690" height="920" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/1aec020164c4cd30cb05a7e9d07b8038393fc93d_2_690x920.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/1aec020164c4cd30cb05a7e9d07b8038393fc93d_2_1035x1380.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/1aec020164c4cd30cb05a7e9d07b8038393fc93d_2_1380x1840.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/1aec020164c4cd30cb05a7e9d07b8038393fc93d_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
</li>
</ol>
<h1>Overnight Preheat (Candle)</h1>
<ol>
<li>
<p>Make sure all gas valves are closed in off position.  Off position is 90 degrees.<br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/01a00bebdfaf1ab7748e5c89db3e5467cd10b750.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/01a00bebdfaf1ab7748e5c89db3e5467cd10b750" title="SON09584.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/01a00bebdfaf1ab7748e5c89db3e5467cd10b750_2_690x459.jpeg" alt="SON09584" width="690" height="459" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/01a00bebdfaf1ab7748e5c89db3e5467cd10b750_2_690x459.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/01a00bebdfaf1ab7748e5c89db3e5467cd10b750_2_1035x688.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/01a00bebdfaf1ab7748e5c89db3e5467cd10b750_2_1380x918.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/01a00bebdfaf1ab7748e5c89db3e5467cd10b750_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>We use a magnet to cover the blower fans, adjusting their power.  For the candle, just cover the fans completely.<br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/79f23188b45e0c9d246f572634b8e74b85e9a4be.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/79f23188b45e0c9d246f572634b8e74b85e9a4be" title="SON09585.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/79f23188b45e0c9d246f572634b8e74b85e9a4be_2_690x459.jpeg" alt="SON09585" width="690" height="459" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/79f23188b45e0c9d246f572634b8e74b85e9a4be_2_690x459.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/79f23188b45e0c9d246f572634b8e74b85e9a4be_2_1035x688.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/79f23188b45e0c9d246f572634b8e74b85e9a4be_2_1380x918.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/79f23188b45e0c9d246f572634b8e74b85e9a4be_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Open the damper to 3/4" or 1".<br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/28f4107ecfd303c9cb42b385c540cb71c00068e4.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/28f4107ecfd303c9cb42b385c540cb71c00068e4" title="IMG_8592.JPG"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/28f4107ecfd303c9cb42b385c540cb71c00068e4_2_690x517.jpeg" alt="IMG_8592" width="690" height="517" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/28f4107ecfd303c9cb42b385c540cb71c00068e4_2_690x517.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/28f4107ecfd303c9cb42b385c540cb71c00068e4_2_1035x775.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/28f4107ecfd303c9cb42b385c540cb71c00068e4_2_1380x1034.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/28f4107ecfd303c9cb42b385c540cb71c00068e4_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Turn on the blower fan.<br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/576e9a1d17ea866f6fc440069bb38bb838a0f83f.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/576e9a1d17ea866f6fc440069bb38bb838a0f83f" title="IMG_8598.JPG"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/576e9a1d17ea866f6fc440069bb38bb838a0f83f_2_690x517.jpeg" alt="IMG_8598" width="690" height="517" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/576e9a1d17ea866f6fc440069bb38bb838a0f83f_2_690x517.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/576e9a1d17ea866f6fc440069bb38bb838a0f83f_2_1035x775.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/576e9a1d17ea866f6fc440069bb38bb838a0f83f_2_1380x1034.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/576e9a1d17ea866f6fc440069bb38bb838a0f83f_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The pilot lights are Venturi burners.  The oxygen to these burners is controlled by the air baffle.  Open the air baffles to about 1/8".<br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/c3c11bde8e412ddf541fce0ead0494a8b2413e87.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/c3c11bde8e412ddf541fce0ead0494a8b2413e87" title="IMG_8596.JPG"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/c3c11bde8e412ddf541fce0ead0494a8b2413e87_2_690x517.jpeg" alt="IMG_8596" width="690" height="517" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/c3c11bde8e412ddf541fce0ead0494a8b2413e87_2_690x517.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/c3c11bde8e412ddf541fce0ead0494a8b2413e87_2_1035x775.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/c3c11bde8e412ddf541fce0ead0494a8b2413e87_2_1380x1034.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/c3c11bde8e412ddf541fce0ead0494a8b2413e87_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Open the pilot light small gas valve halfway.  While pressing the Baso safety valve button, light the pilot.  Keep the Baso button held until the thermocouple is warmed up and the gas does not automatically shut off.  This make take 30-60 seconds.<br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/cda5fe6a4237f4748002b52623137c1102f5b639.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/cda5fe6a4237f4748002b52623137c1102f5b639" title="SON09601.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/cda5fe6a4237f4748002b52623137c1102f5b639_2_690x459.jpeg" alt="SON09601" width="690" height="459" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/cda5fe6a4237f4748002b52623137c1102f5b639_2_690x459.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/cda5fe6a4237f4748002b52623137c1102f5b639_2_1035x688.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/cda5fe6a4237f4748002b52623137c1102f5b639_2_1380x918.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/cda5fe6a4237f4748002b52623137c1102f5b639_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Using the air baffle, adjust the oxygen intake until the flame is blue and gentle.  Too much air = bright, noisy and short flame.  Too little air = yellow, smokey, silent long flame.<br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/c85375179194fefd375e53ef7c3509037902c315.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/c85375179194fefd375e53ef7c3509037902c315" title="SON09596.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/c85375179194fefd375e53ef7c3509037902c315_2_690x459.jpeg" alt="SON09596" width="690" height="459" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/c85375179194fefd375e53ef7c3509037902c315_2_690x459.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/c85375179194fefd375e53ef7c3509037902c315_2_1035x688.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/c85375179194fefd375e53ef7c3509037902c315_2_1380x918.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/c85375179194fefd375e53ef7c3509037902c315_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Ideally you will slowly heat the kiln with only the pilots for a few hours until 400-500 degrees F.  After this time you can light the forced-air burners as well.  To light the forced-air burners, just open the burner gas valve until the burner lights.  Then, adjust the gas back down to about 5 on the gas gauge.  Finally, adjust the air by moving the magnet on the air blower.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h1>Firing (the next day)</h1>
<p>As early as possible on the next morning, increase gas to 10-15, and then adjust the air accordingly.  Ideally the kiln will already be 1300-1400 degrees at this point.  You will need to keep increasing the gas pressure each hour until it’s around 25.  This amount of gas should get you to cone 08.<br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/ae3a0bccdaf55aeac5305298e88a1f9d79938be8.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/ae3a0bccdaf55aeac5305298e88a1f9d79938be8" title="SON09613.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ae3a0bccdaf55aeac5305298e88a1f9d79938be8_2_690x459.jpeg" alt="SON09613" width="690" height="459" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ae3a0bccdaf55aeac5305298e88a1f9d79938be8_2_690x459.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ae3a0bccdaf55aeac5305298e88a1f9d79938be8_2_1035x688.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ae3a0bccdaf55aeac5305298e88a1f9d79938be8_2_1380x918.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ae3a0bccdaf55aeac5305298e88a1f9d79938be8_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
<h1>Reduction</h1>
<ol>
<li>
<p>Starting reduction.  At around 1700-1750, cone 08 should go down.  At this point we will start reduction.  Close the damper to the “BR” line (about 1/2") and increase the gas on both burners to 55.  Adjust the forced air until the burner is no longer noisy (oxygen-rich).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>A few minutes after starting reduction you should definitely notice flame coming out of the top peep hole.  Then you will notice the flame from the side peep hole, and finally you should see a small flame from the bottom peep hole.  While it is not imperative that the bottom peep has a flame, a small flame there will signify that you are definitely getting reduction throughout the entire kiln.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>After one hour of <em>body reduction</em>, you can ease off on the kiln pressure in order to maintain a <em>climbing reduction</em>.  To lower pressure, either back off on the gas (from 55 to 50), or open the damper slightly (from 1/2" to 5/8").  After easing off pressure, make sure that you still see a flame coming from the peeps.  If there is no longer a flame at the peeps, it’s possible you have gone into a neutral to oxidizing atmosphere.  If this is the case, you will need to add more pressure by either increasing the gas or closing the damper slightly.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>After about 2050 degrees you shouldn’t need to touch the kiln.  Just let it fire with the same input settings (gas at about 54, damper at 3/8").  The rate of temperature rise will start to slow down, which is good.  At this point we want it to take at least an hour between cones.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>At around 2250 degrees as indicated by the thermocouple, cone 10 should bend to about 4 o’clock.  At this point we are basically done with our firing.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h1>Oxidation hold</h1>
<p>Many potters end a reduction firing with an <em>oxidation hold</em>.  An oxidation hold is simply a period of oxidation firing.  In order to do this, slowly back off on the gas until the temperature is no longer rising.  Maintain this temperature at the lowest possible gas setting (usually around 25 for Meatball).  After 15-30 minutes, you should notice that cone 10 has completely dropped.  You can now stop the kiln.</p>
<h1>End of firing</h1>
<p>The end of the firing is very important:</p>
<ol>
<li>Turn off all gas valves.</li>
<li>Close damper.</li>
<li>Block off burner ports with a piece of kiln shelf.</li>
</ol>
<h1>Logging and Charting the Firing</h1>
<p>It’s very important to keep accurate logs of a kiln firing so that you understand how a kiln is behaving, and so that you can create firing profiles for kilns that, when followed, lead to consistent, repeatable results.</p>
<p>First, I suggest using a time-series kiln chart.  You can download and print out the charts that I use here:  <a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/kiln-charts/601" class="inline-onebox">Kiln Charts</a></p>
<p></p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/40264731e885f207bab8281d50b51c7d7a938cdc.png" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/40264731e885f207bab8281d50b51c7d7a938cdc" title="Firing_Chart_Fahrenheit.png"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/40264731e885f207bab8281d50b51c7d7a938cdc_2_690x533.png" alt="Firing_Chart_Fahrenheit" width="690" height="533" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/40264731e885f207bab8281d50b51c7d7a938cdc_2_690x533.png, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/40264731e885f207bab8281d50b51c7d7a938cdc_2_1035x799.png 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/40264731e885f207bab8281d50b51c7d7a938cdc_2_1380x1066.png 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/40264731e885f207bab8281d50b51c7d7a938cdc_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
<p>Because this is a time-series chart, the columns represent time in 15-minute segments.  At the bottom of this sheet you can write the time- every four columns is one hour.</p>
<p>After a number of firings, you should be able to compare results and develop a firing profile.  For example, here are 7 firings stacked on top of one another:<br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/4e6ef9d519189075b028d4fb170cf5f91f84ffb1.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/4e6ef9d519189075b028d4fb170cf5f91f84ffb1" title="MeatballAllSingle.JPG"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/4e6ef9d519189075b028d4fb170cf5f91f84ffb1_2_690x690.jpeg" alt="MeatballAllSingle" width="690" height="690" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/4e6ef9d519189075b028d4fb170cf5f91f84ffb1_2_690x690.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/4e6ef9d519189075b028d4fb170cf5f91f84ffb1_2_1035x1035.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/4e6ef9d519189075b028d4fb170cf5f91f84ffb1.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/4e6ef9d519189075b028d4fb170cf5f91f84ffb1_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
<p>From these 7 firings we can develop a firing profile for this kiln:<br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/ed67e7fdc6e7975a7a99aad8a1d58726a51e6152.png" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/ed67e7fdc6e7975a7a99aad8a1d58726a51e6152" title="Firing_Chart_Fahrenheit_Meatball.png"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ed67e7fdc6e7975a7a99aad8a1d58726a51e6152_2_690x533.png" alt="Firing_Chart_Fahrenheit_Meatball" width="690" height="533" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ed67e7fdc6e7975a7a99aad8a1d58726a51e6152_2_690x533.png, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ed67e7fdc6e7975a7a99aad8a1d58726a51e6152_2_1035x799.png 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ed67e7fdc6e7975a7a99aad8a1d58726a51e6152_2_1380x1066.png 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ed67e7fdc6e7975a7a99aad8a1d58726a51e6152_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
<p>Download the firing profile for Meatball here:<br>
<a class="attachment" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/3516f53fe7c2ad449b726f0d85336e33fffdfc44.pdf">Firing_Chart_Fahrenheit_Meatball.pdf</a> (872.7 KB)</p>
<h1>Resources</h1>
<h3>Firing the ACC Downdraft Kiln by Vince Pitelka, 2016</h3>
<p></p><aside class="onebox pdf">
  <header class="source">
      <a href="https://sites.tntech.edu/wpitelka/wp-content/uploads/sites/45/2016/10/Firing-the-ACC-Downdraft.pdf" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">sites.tntech.edu</a>
  </header>
  <article class="onebox-body">
    <a href="https://sites.tntech.edu/wpitelka/wp-content/uploads/sites/45/2016/10/Firing-the-ACC-Downdraft.pdf" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener"><span class="pdf-onebox-logo"></span></a>
<h3><a href="https://sites.tntech.edu/wpitelka/wp-content/uploads/sites/45/2016/10/Firing-the-ACC-Downdraft.pdf" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">Firing-the-ACC-Downdraft.pdf</a></h3>

<p class="filesize">412.11 KB</p>

  </article>
  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>
  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
<br>
Local copy:<br>
<a class="attachment" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/e62800e27594e17b286ab68d172adcdef22718f9.pdf">Firing-the-ACC-Downdraft.pdf</a> (412.1 KB)<p></p>
            <p><small>2 posts - 2 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/firing-cone-10-reduction-in-a-small-gas-kiln-meatball/733">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/firing-cone-10-reduction-in-a-small-gas-kiln-meatball/733</link>
          <pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2019 15:13:56 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-topic-733</guid>
          <source url="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/firing-cone-10-reduction-in-a-small-gas-kiln-meatball/733.rss">Firing Cone 10 Reduction in a Small Gas Kiln, &quot;Meatball&quot;</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Matte Glazes: some info by Pete Pinnell</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[derek]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Glaze Effects</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Pete Pinnell Hi Alisa- these are great looking tests. I can provide you with a bit of background information if you’re interested. Matte glazes tend to get their character from the choice of alkaline earth flux, and there are four of them: barium oxide, strontium oxide, calcium oxide and magnesium oxide. Of course we can source each of these as a simple carbonate, which makes substitutions and comparisons pretty easy. Generally speaking, the brightest results come from barium, with color intensity diminishing from barium, then strontium, calcium, and with magnesium having the lowest color response (one exception to this rule is cobalt in magnesium, which can make intense purple violets, which I find hideous, but some people like). As for surfaces in a matte glaze, magnesium has the smoothest matte surfaces, with calcium being second smoothest, then strontium and then barium being somewhat abrasive (which is why you probably wouldn’t want barium on a food contact surface even if it was safe, which it is not). Lithium (in the form of lithium carbonate) can be added to any of these matte glazes to get the surface a bit more active and visually broken (texture). Lithium can also intensify color a bit and will tend to lower maturing temperature a bit. As for substituting them, you can’t do a gram per gram sub if you want to get a good comparison, because they have very different weights. One molecule of one alkaline earth will have about the same fluxing power as one molecule of a different alkaline earth, even if they are different sizes. Think about a plum compared with an apple. Each is one “unit” of fruit, but a pound of plums will contain more “units” than a pound of apples, so if you want the same number of molecules then you have to make a molecular substitution. If you made a weight substitution, a pound of plums contains a lot more than a pound of apples, even though they weigh the same. Magnesium carbonate has a molecular weight of 84, calcium carbonate 100, strontium carbonate 148, and barium carbonate 197 (these numbers are all rounded). So, begin with a recipe that calls for barium carbonate. To replace the barium with the same amount of strontium, multiply the barium times .75. To replace the strontium with calcium, multiply the strontium times .65. To replace the calcium with magnesium, multiply the calcium times .84. Leave the amounts of the other ingredients the same. This way you’ll have the same amount of alkaline earth flux (on a molecular basis) in each set of tests. In your first test (pictured at the top), you have one third more flux in the glaze with calcium than in the strontium glaze, because calcium that much smaller of a molecule. That is the cause of some of your variation, not just the choice of flux. BTW, you can always mix fluxes to get different qualities. Calcium and magnesium together give smoother, more predictable results than either alone. I like strontium because it provides a fairly smooth surface with good color variation and a pleasant color response. It’s not as intense as barium, but brighter (and easier to control) than a straight calcium matte. On the other hand, a calcium matte (without magnesium) can give a smooth matte that has an almost teflon-like smoothness. Magnesium+calcium mattes tend to just be white, beige, tan or gray. On the other hand, they can have the kind of smooth, buttery surface that causes people to pick the pot up and start moaning with pleasure at the feel. It’s the kind of thing that causes people to make “baby’s bottom” analogies. I hope this helps. Please post the other tests when you fire them. Thanks for doing this!</p>
            <p><small>2 posts - 2 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/matte-glazes-some-info-by-pete-pinnell/578">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/matte-glazes-some-info-by-pete-pinnell/578</link>
          <pubDate>Tue, 07 Aug 2018 01:33:04 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-topic-578</guid>
          <source url="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/matte-glazes-some-info-by-pete-pinnell/578.rss">Matte Glazes: some info by Pete Pinnell</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Drippy Glazes</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[ceramicswiki]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Glaze Effects</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <h2>Possible ways to make drippy glazes</h2>
<p>From John Britt:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You can do it with any very viscous glaze at any temp with some easy experimentation. For cone 10 you want high feldspar so a Kuan glaze…low fire is easy with frit 3124 (which is a great cone 6 glaze with 20% EPK.) I will try to find my Bubble Gum Series…which is a version of this line…</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<h2>Pottery with drips</h2>
<p>Various Chinese ceramics- natural ash glazes, Tenmoku and Jun (Chun)<br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/1e4f37737d4ba761d9fd787b3f52303ce8974054.jpg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/1e4f37737d4ba761d9fd787b3f52303ce8974054" title="IMG_5075_full.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/1e4f37737d4ba761d9fd787b3f52303ce8974054_2_666x500.jpg" width="666" height="500" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/1e4f37737d4ba761d9fd787b3f52303ce8974054_2_666x500.jpg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/1e4f37737d4ba761d9fd787b3f52303ce8974054_2_999x750.jpg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/1e4f37737d4ba761d9fd787b3f52303ce8974054_2_1332x1000.jpg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/1e4f37737d4ba761d9fd787b3f52303ce8974054_2_10x10.png"></a></div><br>
Sui Dynasty Alms Bowl from <a href="http://www.mfa.org/collections/publications/earth-transformed" rel="nofollow noopener">Earth Transformed</a><p></p>
<hr>
<h2>Contemporary Ceramics</h2>
<p><strong>Christina Schou Christensen</strong><br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/521ec625a5fc682354a04f0eca94c273789dae06.jpg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/521ec625a5fc682354a04f0eca94c273789dae06" title="tre_taarne_web.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/521ec625a5fc682354a04f0eca94c273789dae06_2_412x500.jpg" width="412" height="500" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/521ec625a5fc682354a04f0eca94c273789dae06_2_412x500.jpg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/521ec625a5fc682354a04f0eca94c273789dae06_2_618x750.jpg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/521ec625a5fc682354a04f0eca94c273789dae06_2_824x1000.jpg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/521ec625a5fc682354a04f0eca94c273789dae06_2_10x10.png"></a></div><br>
<a href="http://christinaschouchristensen.dk/galleri.htm" class="onebox" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">http://christinaschouchristensen.dk/galleri.htm</a><p></p>
<p><strong>Takuro Kuwata 桑田卓郎</strong><br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/e89dd72374721b209c9aa4914d24a3187e0801b6.jpg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/e89dd72374721b209c9aa4914d24a3187e0801b6" title="takuro-kuwata_03.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/e89dd72374721b209c9aa4914d24a3187e0801b6_2_558x499.jpg" width="558" height="499" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/e89dd72374721b209c9aa4914d24a3187e0801b6_2_558x499.jpg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/e89dd72374721b209c9aa4914d24a3187e0801b6_2_837x748.jpg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/e89dd72374721b209c9aa4914d24a3187e0801b6.jpg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/e89dd72374721b209c9aa4914d24a3187e0801b6_2_10x10.png"></a></div><br>
<aside class="onebox whitelistedgeneric">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://d1s2w0upia4e9w.cloudfront.net/images/favicon.ico" class="site-icon" width="64" height="64">
      <a href="https://www.artsy.net/artist/takuro-kuwata-sang-tian-zhuo-lang" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">artsy.net</a>
  </header>
  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:640/512;"><img src="https://d32dm0rphc51dk.cloudfront.net/DswY_I-CaWvY9RZT7yLmaA/large.jpg" class="thumbnail"></div>

<h3><a href="https://www.artsy.net/artist/takuro-kuwata-sang-tian-zhuo-lang" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">Takuro Kuwata 桑田卓郎 - 58 Artworks, Bio &amp; Shows on Artsy</a></h3>

<p>Find the latest shows, biography, and artworks for sale by Takuro Kuwata 桑田卓郎. Takuro Kuwata is a radical potter who nevertheless describes his work as firml…</p>


  </article>
  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>
  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
<p></p>
<p><strong>Brian Giniewski</strong><br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/15cfebeb58463d3ac19fc29872be884bae9de5b2.jpg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/15cfebeb58463d3ac19fc29872be884bae9de5b2" title="dipped-4.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/15cfebeb58463d3ac19fc29872be884bae9de5b2.jpg" width="500" height="500" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/15cfebeb58463d3ac19fc29872be884bae9de5b2_2_10x10.png"></a></div><br>
<aside class="onebox whitelistedgeneric">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://www.thisiscolossal.com/favicon.ico" class="site-icon" width="48" height="48">
      <a href="https://www.thisiscolossal.com/2017/03/rainbow-drip-vessels-by-brian-giniewski-ceramics/" target="_blank" title="03:37PM - 20 March 2017" rel="nofollow noopener">Colossal – 20 Mar 17</a>
  </header>
  <article class="onebox-body">
    <img src="https://www.thisiscolossal.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/dipped-4.jpg" class="thumbnail onebox-avatar" width="690" height="690">

<h3><a href="https://www.thisiscolossal.com/2017/03/rainbow-drip-vessels-by-brian-giniewski-ceramics/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">Rainbow Drip Vessels by Brian Giniewski Ceramics</a></h3>

<p>Ceramic artist Brian Giniewski produces delightful earthenware vessels that appear to be oozing thick, colorful drips that are frozen in time. The Philadelphia-based ceramicist achieves the texture of the vases and bowls by applying a gritty, matte...</p>


  </article>
  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>
  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
<br>
<aside class="onebox whitelistedgeneric">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://static1.squarespace.com/static/56508fc1e4b085e3bb8334a9/t/59d992168fd4d21d6a596e35/favicon.ico" class="site-icon" width="600" height="600">
      <a href="https://www.brianginiewski.com/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">Brian Giniewski</a>
  </header>
  <article class="onebox-body">
    

<h3><a href="https://www.brianginiewski.com/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">Brian Giniewski</a></h3>

<p>Colorful, drippy + happy ceramics made in Philadelphia, PA USA!</p>


  </article>
  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>
  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
<p></p>
<p><strong>Drew Liedtke</strong><br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/a40eb49d9d8266c6e82b4ccfe2e234f2da443333.jpg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/a40eb49d9d8266c6e82b4ccfe2e234f2da443333" title="l_6172.58141f1b167cf.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/a40eb49d9d8266c6e82b4ccfe2e234f2da443333_2_666x500.jpg" width="666" height="500" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/a40eb49d9d8266c6e82b4ccfe2e234f2da443333_2_666x500.jpg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/a40eb49d9d8266c6e82b4ccfe2e234f2da443333_2_999x750.jpg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/a40eb49d9d8266c6e82b4ccfe2e234f2da443333.jpg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/a40eb49d9d8266c6e82b4ccfe2e234f2da443333_2_10x10.png"></a></div><br>
<a href="https://glazy.org/u/liedtkeclay" class="onebox" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">https://glazy.org/u/liedtkeclay</a><p></p>
<p><strong>Branon Mercer</strong><br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/84bbd6c4403c534c3936d2098d2953fb760f282d.jpg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/84bbd6c4403c534c3936d2098d2953fb760f282d" title="2_Branan_Mercer_contemporary_ceramic_art.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/84bbd6c4403c534c3936d2098d2953fb760f282d_2_500x500.jpg" width="500" height="500" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/84bbd6c4403c534c3936d2098d2953fb760f282d_2_500x500.jpg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/84bbd6c4403c534c3936d2098d2953fb760f282d_2_750x750.jpg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/84bbd6c4403c534c3936d2098d2953fb760f282d_2_1000x1000.jpg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/84bbd6c4403c534c3936d2098d2953fb760f282d_2_10x10.png"></a></div><br>
<a href="https://cfileonline.org/branan-mercer-contemporary-pottery/" class="onebox" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">https://cfileonline.org/branan-mercer-contemporary-pottery/</a><p></p>
<p><strong>Shiyuan Xu</strong><br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/33308e9dedd918e8acc78ea905a2a48e9030802c.jpg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/33308e9dedd918e8acc78ea905a2a48e9030802c" title="s-xu2_orig.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/33308e9dedd918e8acc78ea905a2a48e9030802c.jpg" width="666" height="500" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/33308e9dedd918e8acc78ea905a2a48e9030802c_2_10x10.png"></a></div><br>
<aside class="onebox whitelistedgeneric">
  <header class="source">
      <a href="http://www.shiyuanxu.com" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">SHIYUAN XU</a>
  </header>
  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/459;"><img src="http://www.shiyuanxu.com/uploads/3/7/6/9/37699463/homeage_orig.jpg" class="thumbnail"></div>

<h3><a href="http://www.shiyuanxu.com" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">SHIYUAN XU</a></h3>

<p>SHIYUAN XU</p>


  </article>
  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>
  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
<p></p>
<p><strong>Emily Gardiner</strong><br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/4e00e7b911d96211ac3e71c2a59301e10112b79a.jpg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/4e00e7b911d96211ac3e71c2a59301e10112b79a" title="4631575329.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/4e00e7b911d96211ac3e71c2a59301e10112b79a_2_690x282.jpg" width="690" height="282" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/4e00e7b911d96211ac3e71c2a59301e10112b79a_2_690x282.jpg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/4e00e7b911d96211ac3e71c2a59301e10112b79a.jpg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/4e00e7b911d96211ac3e71c2a59301e10112b79a.jpg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/4e00e7b911d96211ac3e71c2a59301e10112b79a_2_10x10.png"></a></div><br>
<a href="http://www.emilygardiner.com" class="onebox" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">http://www.emilygardiner.com</a><p></p>
<p><strong>Yih-Wen Kuo</strong><br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/c3e9b2b327fe325aeed319722fd3769af3271296.jpg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/c3e9b2b327fe325aeed319722fd3769af3271296" title="2975067920_e42c799d34_b.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/c3e9b2b327fe325aeed319722fd3769af3271296.jpg" width="666" height="500" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/c3e9b2b327fe325aeed319722fd3769af3271296_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
<p><strong>Harris Deller</strong><br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/a340f0ab3e6b656d65755e4afe213710929637bf.jpg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/a340f0ab3e6b656d65755e4afe213710929637bf" title="Screen Shot 2017-04-25 at 1.38.06 AM copy.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/a340f0ab3e6b656d65755e4afe213710929637bf_2_443x500.jpg" width="443" height="500" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/a340f0ab3e6b656d65755e4afe213710929637bf_2_443x500.jpg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/a340f0ab3e6b656d65755e4afe213710929637bf_2_664x750.jpg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/a340f0ab3e6b656d65755e4afe213710929637bf_2_886x1000.jpg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/a340f0ab3e6b656d65755e4afe213710929637bf_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
<p><strong>Jung-yu Tsai</strong><br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/12b8c2d3c0d6dd4ce0d0e643c5b729334d736d6b.jpg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/12b8c2d3c0d6dd4ce0d0e643c5b729334d736d6b" title="tumblr_ng61ewghui1tstv87o1_1280.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/12b8c2d3c0d6dd4ce0d0e643c5b729334d736d6b_2_690x441.jpg" width="690" height="441" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/12b8c2d3c0d6dd4ce0d0e643c5b729334d736d6b_2_690x441.jpg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/12b8c2d3c0d6dd4ce0d0e643c5b729334d736d6b_2_1035x661.jpg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/12b8c2d3c0d6dd4ce0d0e643c5b729334d736d6b.jpg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/12b8c2d3c0d6dd4ce0d0e643c5b729334d736d6b_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
<p><strong>John Britt</strong><br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/ba73c0da49bf843d2810d460e7df16953572f2e8.jpg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/ba73c0da49bf843d2810d460e7df16953572f2e8" title="17992173_10212145944661546_5649779047974655429_n.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/ba73c0da49bf843d2810d460e7df16953572f2e8.jpg" width="690" height="483" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ba73c0da49bf843d2810d460e7df16953572f2e8_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
<p><strong>Kato Tsubusa</strong><br>
</p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/1fbc2b672cd79aadeb94fef85e5482c26866671f.jpg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/1fbc2b672cd79aadeb94fef85e5482c26866671f" title="kato20tsubusa202.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/1fbc2b672cd79aadeb94fef85e5482c26866671f_2_623x499.jpg" width="623" height="499" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/1fbc2b672cd79aadeb94fef85e5482c26866671f_2_623x499.jpg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/1fbc2b672cd79aadeb94fef85e5482c26866671f_2_934x748.jpg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/1fbc2b672cd79aadeb94fef85e5482c26866671f.jpg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/1fbc2b672cd79aadeb94fef85e5482c26866671f_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
<p>Lauren Mabry<br>
</p><aside class="onebox whitelistedgeneric">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://static1.squarespace.com/static/51fc07ebe4b0cd07f0f2e6ae/t/5b968a9e88251b7b969f1542/favicon.ico" class="site-icon" width="294" height="268">
      <a href="http://laurenmabry.com" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">LAUREN MABRY</a>
  </header>
  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/334;"><img src="http://static1.squarespace.com/static/51fc07ebe4b0cd07f0f2e6ae/t/58cae42b6b8f5b831449f616/1489691695804/Lauren+Mabry+logo.jpg?format=1500w" class="thumbnail"></div>

<h3><a href="http://laurenmabry.com" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">LAUREN MABRY</a></h3>

<p>Lauren Mabry is an american artist based out of Philadelphia, Pa. Her primary focus is ceramic sculpture.  Glaze | Material | Movement | Color | Ceramics</p>


  </article>
  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>
  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>
<br>
<div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/ab788ffab899a6e78dfdf07f68c5321e2e70fd84.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/ab788ffab899a6e78dfdf07f68c5321e2e70fd84" title="loopy cylinder pastel 13x14x14 01.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ab788ffab899a6e78dfdf07f68c5321e2e70fd84_2_690x552.jpeg" alt="loopy%20cylinder%20pastel%2013x14x14%2001" width="690" height="552" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ab788ffab899a6e78dfdf07f68c5321e2e70fd84_2_690x552.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ab788ffab899a6e78dfdf07f68c5321e2e70fd84_2_1035x828.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ab788ffab899a6e78dfdf07f68c5321e2e70fd84_2_1380x1104.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ab788ffab899a6e78dfdf07f68c5321e2e70fd84_2_10x10.png"></a></div><br>
<div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/a4f9162c2746aaf56fdaa57e078842f05c9fe2d1.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/a4f9162c2746aaf56fdaa57e078842f05c9fe2d1" title="Untitled (Brick Piece) 01.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/a4f9162c2746aaf56fdaa57e078842f05c9fe2d1_2_690x552.jpeg" alt="Untitled%20(Brick%20Piece)%2001" width="690" height="552" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/a4f9162c2746aaf56fdaa57e078842f05c9fe2d1_2_690x552.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/a4f9162c2746aaf56fdaa57e078842f05c9fe2d1_2_1035x828.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/a4f9162c2746aaf56fdaa57e078842f05c9fe2d1_2_1380x1104.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/a4f9162c2746aaf56fdaa57e078842f05c9fe2d1_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/drippy-glazes/96">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/drippy-glazes/96</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2017 16:19:06 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-topic-96</guid>
          <source url="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/drippy-glazes/96.rss">Drippy Glazes</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>About the Glaze Effects category</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[ceramicswiki]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Glaze Effects</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Contemporary ceramicists are pushing the extremes of glazes.  Here’s a place to talk about various glaze effects.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/about-the-glaze-effects-category/95">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/about-the-glaze-effects-category/95</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2017 16:06:31 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>Yes</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-topic-95</guid>
          <source url="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/about-the-glaze-effects-category/95.rss">About the Glaze Effects category</source>
        </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
