<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:discourse="http://www.discourse.org/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Clay Bodies - Glazy Ceramics Wiki</title>
    <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/c/clay-bodies/17</link>
    <description>Topics in the &#39;Clay Bodies&#39; category </description>
    
      <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2019 23:17:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <atom:link href="https://wiki.glazy.org/c/clay-bodies/17.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        <item>
          <title>Ultra-high Temperature Ceramics</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[noships]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Clay Bodies</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Ultra-high Temperature Ceramics<br>
N. Shipley</p>
<p><strong>Introduction</strong><br>
The highest cone that exists on the pyrometric chart is ∆42. This temperature only exists in the creation of certain industrial ceramics, and for all intents and purposes is something the ordinary ceramicist will never encounter. However, certain types of ceramics can function well above ∆42! These types of ceramics are referred to as <em>ultra-high temperature ceramics</em>, or UHTCs for short. UHTCs are surprisingly hard to define, so three different definitions will be provided:</p>
<ol>
<li>UHTCs are ceramic materials that melt above 3000˚C.</li>
<li>UHTCs are ceramic materials that are available for use in air above 1600-2000˚C.</li>
<li>UHTCs are any compound that contains a transition metal (Zr, Hf, Ta, W, or Nb) along with B, C, or N (Fahrenholtz).</li>
</ol>
<p>Each of these definitions has its own limitations. To start, only W, Ta, or Re meet the first criterion, that the material must melt above 3000˚C. The second definition is helpful from an engineering standpoint, but depends greatly on the length of time the material is exposed to air. The third definition is the most widely used, but falls short when it is applied to composite UHTCs, such as ZrB2 – SiC (Fahrenholtz).</p>
<p>UHTCs have been known by different names, including “refractory borides,” or “refractory carbides,” “oxidation-resistant diborides,” “ceramals,” “cermets,” and “hard metals”. The term “ultra-high temperature ceramics” has only become popular in the past 20-30 years as interest in and research on the materials has increased (Fahrenholtz).</p>
<p><strong>History</strong><br>
The story of UHTCs is fascinating and checkered, and cannot be told without delving into the Cold War, the space race, or the U.S. military. The precursor of some of the most widely-used UHTCs, ZrB2, was discovered in 1902 by Samuel A. Tucker and Herbert R. Moody. Although a few initial studies on the material’s bonding and electrical properties were conducted in the following years, by and large the scientific community paid the discovery little attention (Royal Society).</p>
<p>Interest in UHTCs perked up again in the 1950s, as tensions increased between the U.S. and the Soviet Union. The escalating Cold War and concomitant interest in spaceflight pushed scientists to investigate boride and carbide ceramics for their potential use in rocket nozzles. Although no reusable aerospace vehicles at the time reached ultra-high temperatures, NASA scientists realized that future vehicles would likely necessitate advances in materials science (Fahrenholtz).</p>
<p>1960s research by the U.S. Air Force into reusable atmospheric reentry vehicles identified boride ceramics as candidates for leading edge materials, as sharp leading edges of such vehicles can reach temperatures of over 2000˚C. HfB2 and ZrB2 eventually became prime candidates for research and applications in atmospheric reentry (Fahrenholtz). Research by the U.S. military in the 1970s into hypersonic flight likewise advanced the field of UHTCs (Justin and Jankowiak).</p>
<p><strong>Physical Properties</strong><br>
UHTCs can be classified as borides, carbides, or nitrides. They are characterized by their high melting points, high hardness, low reactivity, and (in some cases) resistance to oxidation (Justin and Jankowiak). Each of these categories posses their own strengths and shortcomings.</p>
<p>The borides, such as ZrB2 and HfB2 have hexagonal crystal structures. Their intrinsic thermal conductivities (intrinsic referring to properties that have nothing to do with processing) are quite high. This means that borides are good in applications where there is a large, rapid increase in temperature, such as in rocket nozzles (Wuchina et al). Borides do have some trouble with oxidation, and as such there has been much research into their oxidation resistance. In particular, SiO2-forming species are promising additives, because as the ceramic oxidizes the additives melt and form a protective layer of glass (Wuchina et al).</p>
<p>The carbides have very high melting points—much higher than those of the borides (Table 1). TaC and HfC in particular have been the subject of much research because of their high melting temperature, hardness, and strength. Unfortunately, when in oxidation the carbides are subject to pesting, which is when oxide grains break off instead of densifying. However, this becomes less of a problem when temperatures rapidly increase from a baseline to above 2000˚C, as then the oxides are able to properly densify. As such, carbides are not as useful in leading edges, which are subject to large amounts of oxidation as well as slower increases in temperature, but are useful in low-oxygen environments, as they then perform as well as or better than their boride counterparts (Wuchina et al).</p>
<p>Nitrides are less well-understood than borides or carbides. They have very high melting temperatures: HfN melts at around 3300˚C, and under some conditions can even reach 3800˚C without melting. Nitrides also operate over a range of chemical ratios (stoichiometries). At high temperatures over long periods, nitrides will lose their nitrogen, which can lead to structural failure and disintegration (Wuchina et al).</p>
<p><strong>Preparation, Densification, and Machining</strong><br>
The fabrication of UHTCs begins by creating the precursors, which exist as powders prior to their densification. The powders are typically synthesized through reduction or direct reaction (Wuchina et al). Powder blends are ball-milled to increase particle uniformity and decrease size, and are then sieved (Justin and Jankowiak). The blends are then typically densified by hot-pressing (~1800˚C and ~27MPa) the powder mixtures in graphite molds (Wuchina et al). Currently, there is some research into pressureless spark plasma sintering, which would enable complex shapes and could also be done at lower temperatures. This technique is also promising because it leads to comparatively smaller grain size, which increases the strength of the material (Justin and Jankowiak).</p>
<p>UHTCs are typically either hot-pressed into their desired shapes or machined. Machining is often an expensive, difficult, and unreliable process due to UHTCs’ brittle nature, and is accomplished by grinding with diamond tools. Advances in machining such as electrical discharge machining offers a cheap and precise alternative to typical machining techniques (Justin and Jankowiak).</p>
<p><strong>Health and Safety</strong><br>
The average ceramic artist is unlikely to come into contact with UHTCs, whether it be in the studio or elsewhere. Furthermore, unless one works in the manufacture of UHTCs or in a lab, it is highly unlikely one will come in contact with the materials in their powdered form. That being said, the health effects of powdered UHTCs are either negligible or unknown. Of the two most common UHTC precursors, HfB2 and ZrB2, HfB2 causes skin, eye, and respiratory irritation, while ZrB2 causes only minor irritation. HfB2 is not known to be a carcinogen, and it is unknown whether ZrB2 has carcinogenic properties. ZrB2 is somewhat flammable in its powder form (LTS Laboratory).</p>
<p><strong>Applications</strong><br>
UHTCs are valuable in a wide range of fields, including manufacture, electronics, aerospace, and nuclear energy. In manufacture they are commonly found in furnace elements or refractory crucibles (Justin and Jankowiak). Certain nitride UHTCs are essential in the microelectronics industry, and are used as diffusion barriers—barriers that prevent diffusion between between metal components (Wuchina et al).</p>
<p>Without UHTCs, advances in hypersonic flight and aerospace in general would not have been possible. The sharp aerosurfaces of hypersonic flight vehicles can reach temperatures between 2000˚C and 2400˚C, but must also be able to operate in air and be reusable. These high temperatures occur because thin leading edges increase lift-to-drag ratios, but also increase temperatures. UHTCs are essential in this context because they possess a high thermal conductivity, which reduces thermal stress by decreasing the magnitude of the thermal gradient and allows energy to be conducted away from the edge and be radiated out by materials with lower heat fluxes. In other words, heat travels quickly in UHTCs, which reduces internal stresses and allows the heat to quickly disperse (Justin and Jankowiak).</p>
<p>There is potential for use of UHTCs in nuclear pellets, which currently suffer from poor thermal and structural properties. UHTCs are also potentially fissile and offer superior thermal conductivity and phase stability. Furthermore, advances in nuclear technology, such as the development of Tokamak fusion reactors, will necessitate UHTCs. Tokamaks, which contain plasma within a magnetic field, often reach extreme temperatures on their interiors due to stray neutrons let off by the plasma (Fahrenholtz). Applications such as these are on the cutting edge of materials science, and will likely require huge leaps in scientific knowledge, manufacturing techniques, and materials engineering.</p>
<p><strong>Conclusion</strong><br>
Although the average ceramic artist is unlikely to encounter ultra-high temperature ceramics during their career, it is still worth keeping track of and paying attention to these materials. Their use in industry, warfare, energy, and more irrevocably ties them to the lives of ordinary people, whether they know it or not. It is worth critically examining the histories and uses of these materials in order to uncover their role in global power systems (as for instance in their use in warfare), perpetuation of environmental issues (nuclear reactors), or opportunities for cleaner energy (fusion reactors). Furthermore, their unusual physical properties, fabrication techniques, and histories offer opportunities for artistic inspiration and creation.</p>
<p>.<br>
.<br>
.<br>
.</p>
<p>References<br>
Fahrenholtz, William G. Ultra-High Temperature Ceramics: Materials for Extreme Environment Applications. Hoboken, NJ: Wiley, ACers, 2014.</p>
<p>Royal Society. International Catalogue of Scientific Literature: Chemistry. Vol. 2. International Council, 1904.</p>
<p>Justin, J.F., and A. Jankowiak. “Ultra High Temperature Ceramics: Densification, Properties and Thermal Stability.” The Onera Journal, no. 3 (November 2011).</p>
<p>LTS Research Laboratories, Inc., “Hafnium Diboride.” n.d.</p>
<p>LTS Research Laboratories, Inc., “Zirconium Diboride.” n.d.</p>
<p>Wuchina, E., E. Opila, M. Opeka, W. Fahrenholtz, and I. Talmy. “UHTCs: Ultra-High Temperature Ceramic Materials for Extreme Environment Applications.” The Electrochemical Society, Interface, 2007.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/ultra-high-temperature-ceramics/872">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/ultra-high-temperature-ceramics/872</link>
          <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2019 23:17:03 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-topic-872</guid>
          <source url="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/ultra-high-temperature-ceramics/872.rss">Ultra-high Temperature Ceramics</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Laguna Clays</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[derek]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Commercial Clay Bodies</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <h2>Western Clays</h2>
<h3>Laguna LC-104 Cone 5 Sample Kit</h3>
<p>Oxidation fired color range: white to tans to light browns</p>
<p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/13f619fb7058b73535b210e5c3afe4572b75cfbf.jpeg">Link to original high-resolution image</a></p>
<p></p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/13f619fb7058b73535b210e5c3afe4572b75cfbf.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/13f619fb7058b73535b210e5c3afe4572b75cfbf" title="LagunaC5WhiteClays_lg.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/13f619fb7058b73535b210e5c3afe4572b75cfbf_2_690x690.jpeg" alt="LagunaC5WhiteClays_lg" data-base62-sha1="2QAlctwSWw0gKxiBMQvXe4CLMPZ" width="690" height="690" srcset="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/13f619fb7058b73535b210e5c3afe4572b75cfbf_2_690x690.jpeg, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/13f619fb7058b73535b210e5c3afe4572b75cfbf_2_1035x1035.jpeg 1.5x, https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/13f619fb7058b73535b210e5c3afe4572b75cfbf_2_1380x1380.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/13f619fb7058b73535b210e5c3afe4572b75cfbf_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/laguna-clays/858">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/laguna-clays/858</link>
          <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2019 14:15:42 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-topic-858</guid>
          <source url="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/laguna-clays/858.rss">Laguna Clays</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Types of clay: Know what you’re working with</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[emace]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Clay Bodies</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I have recently taken an Introduction to Clays class, I’m focusing on the formation of clay and looking at specific types of clay. It has been a great experience to go at my own pace and review the material as needed to grasp its content. Being math and chemistry phobic, I have finally grasped some basics of how the elements interact. Knowing this will serve as a valuable tool to be able to achieve a desired effect in working with a clay body. Therefore, I thought I’d write about something I learned and found useful, which just touches on some different types of clay, and is by no means an exhaustive study.</p>
<p>When planning a project, it is important to be aware that some types of clay can be used alone while others, more than likely, will need to be mixed together with other types of clay to some extent to get one’s desired effect. Clays are a naturally occurring composition of elements derived from rocks, they take on different characteristics depending on how the minerals have been acted upon by natural forces, such as wind, rain, freezing, thawing and other weather conditions which help break down the rocks along with other forces like rivers, glaciers and gravity allowing rocks to fall and break apart. This helps clay particles to separate and settle together to make up various deposits.</p>
<p>A particular type of rock, referred to as a Feldspar, is a primary source of silica and<br>
alumina, of which clay is most usually composed. Clay is divided into two groups, primary and secondary. Primary clay refers to clay that has not moved from the location of the<br>
source rock that has decomposed and thus have the least amount of contamination. This is<br>
referred to as kaolin and that is the primary ingredient in porcelain. The theoretically pure<br>
kaolin formula is Al2O3 * 2SiO2 * 2H2O, which is, to the extent of current knowledge, not found in nature; in nature, we are likely to find other trace elements, which would slightly upset the above formula (Rhodes, 2000, p. 28).</p>
<p>Secondary clays are the ones as described as being transported from their source rock<br>
and mixing with other elements. When silica and alumina are combined with other elements, from what is referred to as alkalies, and when all the clay particles are of the optimal ratios, they can be made pliable with the addition of water. They then can be formed into most any shape if manipulated accordingly. Water allows the clay particles to slide along each other like two flat pieces of glass that has a film of water separating them.</p>
<p>Along with the initial groupings of Primary and Secondary exists subgroups of the secondary clay category. These different types can each perform different functions, and, once again, sometimes different clays are mixed together to get a specific response. The following are some different types of clay and a brief description of some of their characteristics.</p>
<p>Ball Clays</p>
<p>The term “ball clay” originates from “an early English clay mining practice of rolling the highly plastic clay into balls weighing 30 to 50 pounds” (Hosterman, 1949, p. C8). Ball clay when damp has the ability to be pressed and made into shapes without cracking. It’s a secondary clay, in that it has been moved by wind or water from its source and settled elsewhere in a deposit, it often contains some organic material. According to Hosterman (1949) “quartz sand or silt and iron oxide minerals are virtually absent from the best grades of ball clay” (p. C8). It is “used in clay bodies to increase plasticity and in glazes to add alumina” and “fires to a grayish or buff color” (Speight, 2003, p.G-1). Its other uses in the ceramic industry include the making of pottery, dinnerware, stoneware, tiles and sanitary ware (Hosterman, 1949, p. C8).</p>
<p>Ball Clay is made up of crystalline kaolinite with small amounts of illite and/or smectite (Hosterman, 1949, p. C1). Illite is defined as “a group name for non-expanding, clay-sized, dioctahedral, micaceous minerals” (USGS). Smectite is defined as “a clay mineral which undergoes reversible expansion on absorbing water” (Lexico). Hosterman (1949) states that “ball clays require 40 and 65 percent water of plasticity to become workable” (p. C8). The most notable characteristics of ball clay include “its plasticity, toughness, high green strength and adhesion” (Hosterman, 1949, p. C8). After firing, ball clay becomes vitreous and dense and the temperatures it melts is between 1,670 and 1,760 degrees Celsius (Hosterman, 1949, p. C8). They are not used by themselves in pottery making due to their characteristic of excessive shrinkage (Rhodes, 2000, p. 68). In fact, ball clays have been known to have shrinkage “as high as 20 percent when fired to maturity” (Rhodes, 2000, p. 68). They are often used as an additive to other clays to achieve “increased plasticity and workability” (Rhodes, 2000, p. 68). If the intended outcome for the clay body color is white, then one should not add above 15 percent of ball clay as anything above that amount tends to turn the fired body “a grey, off-white, or buff color” (Rhodes, 2000, p.68). There are sources of ball clay in the United States, mainly in “Tennessee, Kentucky, Mississippi, Texas, California, and Maryland, with the largest and purest deposits in Tennessee and Kentucky” (Powell, 1995, p. 200).</p>
<p>Fire Clays</p>
<p>Fire clays are aptly named as their distinguishing characteristic is their ability to resist high temperatures more so than the other clay types. Clays that resist fusion or deformity up to around 1500 degrees Celsius can be referred to as a fire clay (Rhodes, 2000, p. 68). They are very useful in the making of fire brick and other parts used in “kilns, furnaces, boilers, and melting pots” (Rhodes, 2000, p. 68 &amp; 69). It can be added to stoneware bodies to help increase its refractoriness and enhance the roughness of the body texture (Rhodes, p.68 &amp; p.69).</p>
<p>Stoneware Clays</p>
<p>Stoneware is a secondary clay formed when one clay’s particles became mixed with clay particles of varying sizes which helps it hold its form (aka plasticity) because the clay particles have more surface contact with each other which is helpful in shaping an object. Iron, titanium, and potassium are fluxes in stoneware. It is important to note that iron and titanium may cause the clay to turn brown when fired. Stoneware can vary in its’ characteristic, depending on where it was harvested. Its’ fired color can vary from buff to brown depending on the iron and titanium content.  It is often used to make coffee mugs, dinner plates, pitchers and many other types of utilitarian wares.  Sometimes it can be used just as found without adding any other ingredients to it (Rhodes, 2000, p. 69). Depending on its composition it can be fired to maturity anywhere between cone 1 to cone 10. (Speight,2003, p.185)</p>
<p>Earthenware Clays</p>
<p>Earthenware clay is a porous secondary clay and is also referred to as a Low-Fire clay. It fires to mature temperatures of cone 010 to cone 1 (Speight, 2003, p. 184). According to Speight (2003), “natural low-fired earthenware varies in color from reddish to yellowish, depending on the amount of iron or lime it contains” (p. 184 &amp; 185). Most clay found in nature might be earthenware clay (Rhodes, 2000, p.69). It is commonly used for making sculpture, flower pots and bricks. (Rhodes, 2000 p.69) (Speight, 2003, p.185).</p>
<p>It’s important to learn some basics about the different kinds of clay, to be able to most effectively choose a material that will help us achieve our desired outcome.</p>
<p>References</p>
<p>Hosterman, J. W. (1949). <em>Ball Clay and Bentonite Deposits of the Central and Eastern Gulf of Mexico Coastal Plain, United States</em> (No. 1558). US Department of the Interior, Geological Survey; Washington, DC.</p>
<p>Lexico Powered by Oxford. (n.d.). Smectite. Retrieved from <a href="https://www.lexico.com/en/definition/smectite" rel="nofollow noopener">https://www.lexico.com/en/definition/smectite</a></p>
<p>Powell, P. S. (1995, January). Ball clay basics. In <em>Ceramic Engineering and Science Proceedings</em> (Vol. 16, No. 3, pp. 200-206).</p>
<p>Rhodes, D. (2000). <em>Clay and glazes for the potter</em> (3rd rev. ed.). London;Iola, Wis;: Krause Publications.</p>
<p>Speight, C. F., &amp; Toki, J. (2003). <em>Hands in clay</em> . McGraw-Hill Humanities/Social Sciences/Languages.</p>
<p>USGS Coastal and Marine Geology Program. (n.d.). Illite Group. Retrieved from <a href="https://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2001/of01-041/htmldocs/clays/illite.htm" rel="nofollow noopener">https://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2001/of01-041/htmldocs/clays/illite.htm</a></p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/types-of-clay-know-what-you-re-working-with/837">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/types-of-clay-know-what-you-re-working-with/837</link>
          <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2019 18:30:41 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-topic-837</guid>
          <source url="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/types-of-clay-know-what-you-re-working-with/837.rss">Types of clay: Know what you’re working with</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>North American Clay Manufacturers</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[katzeye]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Commercial Clay Bodies</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>A list of clay manufacturers, their products, technical specifications, reviews and news.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/north-american-clay-manufacturers/763">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/north-american-clay-manufacturers/763</link>
          <pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2019 20:02:53 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-topic-763</guid>
          <source url="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/north-american-clay-manufacturers/763.rss">North American Clay Manufacturers</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Commercial Clays Manufacturers</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[katzeye]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Commercial Clay Bodies</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>A list of clay manufacturers, their products, technical specifications, reviews and news.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/commercial-clays-manufacturers/761">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/commercial-clays-manufacturers/761</link>
          <pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2019 19:46:37 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-topic-761</guid>
          <source url="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/commercial-clays-manufacturers/761.rss">Commercial Clays Manufacturers</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Mixing my own clay</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[jpib]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Mixing and Reclaiming Clay</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <h5><a href="https://www.facebook.com/profile.php?id=100005075446403&amp;fref=gs&amp;__tn__=%2CdC-R-R&amp;eid=ARBHjscY4TE09YGUyD38-XRHorG4PykkSnlvc61_dVD6yCX0kdGTBmALfmWQDTApyxr2k2hbQFVrU1go&amp;hc_ref=ARQE0NFfxSlDGwQWi1zNOyT2vtdyJij0FYwYBZjYSdTUnhNXqXZUwqfptTxbLqyrQAc&amp;dti=1909393306003874&amp;hc_location=group" rel="nofollow noopener">Gunnar Rasmussen</a></h5>
<p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/opensourceceramics/permalink/2268237546786113/" rel="nofollow noopener">10 novembre, 14:43</a></p>
<p>I am a small time operator, cant aford the pug mills ,claymixers,slab rollers, but i like to mix my own clay, Nd for me this set up works the best for me . I like to wet mix my clay bodys, i get the slurry about as thin as 2% milk and then pour it into this gravity capilary filter drainer, i use Jute twine and put it thru the holes and let it hang down about 1" to wick the water down and drip into the bottom of the bucket , the cloth is old bed sheet as it has fine weave, and only the water passes thru , Now the advantige of wet mixing is better mixing and i pass it thru a 100 mesh seive three times then to the filter , and if the clay has souluble things in it , most of it drains out with the exess water , just thought i would shair with other poor potters who cant aford all the expensive equipment</p>
<p>what you see takes over night and then i set it on a drying batt it goes fairly fast</p>
<p></p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/1f98b1a57b5e0ca858a369be0d3d4b4664028ce3.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/1f98b1a57b5e0ca858a369be0d3d4b4664028ce3" title="image.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/1f98b1a57b5e0ca858a369be0d3d4b4664028ce3.jpeg" alt="image" width="690" height="920" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/1f98b1a57b5e0ca858a369be0d3d4b4664028ce3_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
<p></p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/eb7125bb4de3f268aa3092d182dc695fb8932f5f.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/eb7125bb4de3f268aa3092d182dc695fb8932f5f" title="image.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/eb7125bb4de3f268aa3092d182dc695fb8932f5f.jpeg" alt="image" width="690" height="920" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/eb7125bb4de3f268aa3092d182dc695fb8932f5f_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
<p></p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/ddf5edeeea43729ff16db3291c499283389dba98.jpeg" data-download-href="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/ddf5edeeea43729ff16db3291c499283389dba98" title="image.jpg"><img src="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/original/1X/ddf5edeeea43729ff16db3291c499283389dba98.jpeg" alt="image" width="690" height="920" data-small-upload="https://wiki.glazy.org/uploads/default/optimized/1X/ddf5edeeea43729ff16db3291c499283389dba98_2_10x10.png"></a></div><p></p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/mixing-my-own-clay/620">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/mixing-my-own-clay/620</link>
          <pubDate>Thu, 15 Nov 2018 07:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-topic-620</guid>
          <source url="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/mixing-my-own-clay/620.rss">Mixing my own clay</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Natural clay processing guide</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[derek]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Clay Bodies</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Tim Powers Here is my complete natural clay processing guide I put together.</p>
<p>The natural clay that I use is dug up from my property here at my home. I add water and 2 cups of white vinegar to dissolve calcium and leave it I buckets for several years to grow bacteria, mixing it every few months. When needed I mix it and run it through a screen to remove rocks and organic material. Then I place it on a plaster bat for several days to remove the excess water. Then I wedge it and store it to use as needed. When I fire it, it’s first bisque fired to cone 06. (1830 degrees). Then decorated with glaze and fired again to cone 5 (2185 degrees). It begins to melt around cone 7. It’s a beautiful terra cotta color when bisque fired and an antique copper color when glaze fired. To increase plasticity in this Clay add:</p>
<p>Epsom Salts<br>
Adding about 5 oz of Epsom salts (magnesium sulfate) per 100 lbs of dry clay formula (approximately 0.3% of the formula) can increase plasticity on another level. Epsom salts increase the attraction of clay platelets in the moist clay state and cause the clay to become flocculated. Clay platelets are then drawn together, similar to the way in which the north and south poles of a magnet are attracted and bind together. The overall effect is a tight, plastic clay body with good throwing properties. Each clay body will require a slightly different percentage of Epsom salts due to the individual materials in the formula. Too high a percentage of Epsom salts can cause salt migration to the drying clay surface, which can result in blistering and carbon being trapped in the clay. Adding the Epsom salts to the water and then adding that mixture to the clay mixing operation can help ensure that the salts are dispersed evenly throughout the batch.</p>
<p>Also try:<br>
Organic Agents-<br>
Mold growth in the moist clay can increase plasticity since it increases the binding action or attraction of the clay platelets. When mixing a 100-lb batch of clay formula, add 1/2 cup of beer, coffee or apple cider vinegar, or 3 oz of yeast, to the water before adding the water to the clay. All of these agents will start mold growth in the clay/water mixture. Moist clay kept in a warm, dark place for several days can also be the perfect medium to grow mold.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/natural-clay-processing-guide/577">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/natural-clay-processing-guide/577</link>
          <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2018 11:00:23 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-topic-577</guid>
          <source url="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/natural-clay-processing-guide/577.rss">Natural clay processing guide</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>About the Clay Bodies category</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[derek]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Clay Bodies</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>(Replace this first paragraph with a brief description of your new category. This guidance will appear in the category selection area, so try to keep it below 200 characters. <strong>Until you edit this description or create topics, this category won’t appear on the categories page.</strong>)</p>
<p>Use the following paragraphs for a longer description, or to establish category guidelines or rules:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Why should people use this category? What is it for?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>How exactly is this different than the other categories we already have?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>What should topics in this category generally contain?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Do we need this category? Can we merge with another category, or subcategory?</p>
</li>
</ul>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/about-the-clay-bodies-category/50">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://wiki.glazy.org/t/about-the-clay-bodies-category/50</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2017 00:15:55 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>Yes</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">wiki.glazy.org-topic-50</guid>
          <source url="https://wiki.glazy.org/t/about-the-clay-bodies-category/50.rss">About the Clay Bodies category</source>
        </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
